Today's video is a bit special.
Now, even though this is a members-only video,
But the first 30 minutes are set to be free for everyone to watch.
And that's because we're going to be talking about the Tun Hexagram.
It's the fundamental law and process our ancestors deduced for us, applicable to the initial stage of all things.
If we say that the Qian and Kun hexagrams are the guiding principles for those who aspire to greatness,
So, the Tun Hexagram is the fundamental principle for the beginning of every person's journey that we'll all encounter!
So, if you've ever wondered why everything just feels off when you first enter the workforce or join a new company,
And why is it that, at times like these, people usually just use you as a pawn instead of taking you under their wing as a protégé?
Why is it that after we've worked our butts off for ten years to save up some money,
and pour it all into the stock market, you'll most likely end up weeping tears of blood.
and most likely end up weeping tears of blood.
And why is it that as soon as we start making some headway, we take out loans to massively hire people, bring in new equipment, and expand production capacity?
And then, the orders will suddenly stop coming in, leaving you in a living hell.
And by the end of today's video, we'll have the answers to all these questions.
Thousands of years ago, our ancestors, in the Hexagram of Zhun, had already laid out for us the fundamental principles and boundaries for all our actions.
With the existence of Heaven and Earth, all things are born.
And all things are what fill the space between heaven and earth.
And so, the Hexagram of Zhun follows.
The character 'Zhun' signifies fullness.
It is the beginning of all things.
So, with that, we've covered Qian and Kun, the two parent trigrams.
Now, it's time for life to begin its endless cycle of growth.
The second hexagram in the I Ching is the 'Zhun' hexagram.
As the saying goes, 'Zhun means to be full.'
It signifies the beginning of all things.
It's the stage where all things begin to sprout after the creation of heaven and earth.
a scene of order just beginning to form.
The reason the character '屯' (tún) is pronounced this way here,
The Shuowen Jiezi, an ancient Chinese dictionary, explains: "Tun means difficulty. It is an image of how plants struggle to sprout from the earth, full of hardship."
It describes the scene of a seedling breaking through the soil, pushing aside the earth to sprout for the very first time.
to describe 'the beginning of all things.'
It describes the vitality and hardship of all things in their infancy.
So, let's dive into what we have for you today.
The Tun hexagram is Kan above and Zhen below. Now, Kan and Zhen... do you remember what we said about them in the last episode?
They are the second son and the eldest son.
They are the water of wisdom and the thunder of new life.
That's why the Tun Hexagram is also known as "Water over Thunder."
尊 (zūn)
After the spring thunder roars, all things come back to life.
And the spring rain, as precious as oil, nourishes all things.
However, this is just an interpretation based on the combination of the trigrams' names.
In terms of its imagery, it should be called 'Cloud and Thunder Zhun'.
This is because having Water above Thunder signifies that the rain has not yet fallen.
It means the heavy rain is ready to fall.
This state, where the rain is about to fall but has not yet, is also the state just before the spring rain nourishes all things and new life begins.
This is exactly what's stated in the Great Image Commentary: 'Clouds and thunder in Zhun; the superior person, in the same way, plans and manages affairs.'
And this phrase, 'A noble person acts to bring order to the world,' is also a remarkably insightful summary.
The term 'jinglun' originally referred to the art of weaving.
The 'warp' refers to the vertical threads on a loom that are fixed in place.
It forms the skeleton and backbone of the fabric. Once established,
It runs through the entire process and cannot be altered at will. Otherwise, the fabric will fall apart.
Otherwise, you'll just lose your footing.
The 'weft' refers to the horizontal threads that are woven back and forth in the process of textile making.
It's the thread that weaves the warp threads into a cohesive whole.
This allows it to be flexible and adaptable.
adjusting its density and color as needed.
This term, "Jinglun," is used to describe the very beginning, when all things are just sprouting and fraught with peril.
A person of integrity must bring order to chaos and find a clear path forward.
First, establish the warp of strategy: the unchanging, immutable principles of the right path.
an unchanging and righteous strategic vision.
Then, weave in the weft of tactics—adaptable and situation-specific.
Ultimately, in this state of brewing storm, where clouds and thunder clash but the rain has yet to fall,
an era of 'Zhun' where vitality and chaos coexist.
and emerge from this perilous state, from chaos to order.
Don't worry about being completely in the dark.
So, for the past thirty minutes of content,
The answer to what we should do in the perilous early stages of growth will reveal itself.
Now, let's look at the hexagram statement.
Supreme success, perseverance.
Do not act rashly. It is advantageous to establish a firm foundation.
Now, the phrase 'Yuan Heng Li Zhen' that starts this off should be very familiar to us.
The guiding principle of the 'Zhun Hexagram' is the same as that of the 'Qian Hexagram'.
This means it carries on the virtue of Qian.
"Yuan" signifies the beginning of all things.
The presence of 'Yuan' in the hexagram's statement means that Heaven grants every living being a chance to begin.
This is a crucial point. Take, for instance, the Meng hexagram, which comes later and is about the pursuit of knowledge.
or the Xū hexagram, which is about sustenance.
But none of those have the 'Yuan'.
Not everyone is worthy of being taught.
and those who are nurtured,
The 'Heng' or 'persistence' signifies that as long as you follow the natural way of all things at their inception,
Although it is arduous,
it can still break through obstacles and grow smoothly.
The character 'Li' signifies that during this initial, difficult stage of creation,
it is necessary to pursue what is beneficial and reasonable.
No greed, no delusion.
The term 'Zhēn' refers to the stage of initial creation and establishment.
facing a lack of foundation,
and a host of other adverse factors, like a difficult road ahead.
Only by adhering to the right path can you ensure your survival.
This is the principle we mentioned earlier, "The noble person takes action to bring order to the world."
that unchanging and timeless 'Jing'
So, what exactly is the correct way to navigate the "Zhun" phase?
And the Hexagram Statement immediately provides the answer.
“Do not act rashly. It is favorable to establish a lord.” The first part, “Do not act rashly,” means you shouldn't make any large-scale, aggressive moves.
or acting rashly with blind expansion.
And this is how the Commentary on the Decision explains this line.
Zhun. The firm and the yielding are first in interaction. Difficulty is born of movement within danger, yet it brings great success through perseverance.
In the beginning, when all things are born and first created, they are tender and fragile.
At the very beginning of creation and birth, everything is tender.
and cannot withstand any destruction.
The phrase "movement within danger" describes the characteristics of the Zhen and Kan trigrams.
Zhen represents movement, and Kan represents danger.
Now, let's take a closer look at the character 'Kǎn'.
Now, let's take a closer look at this.
From the very moment this character was created, the meaning of 'danger' has been etched into its core.
has already been etched into its very core.
The Shuowen Jiezi, an ancient Chinese dictionary, states that "Kǎn" means "a pit or a trap."
Its original meaning refers to a sunken, uneven pit or hollow.
In the Bagua, the Kan trigram is used to represent water.
This is also because it is the nature of water to flow downwards.
It will inevitably flow and gather in the lowest, sunken places.
Although water nourishes all things,
But the unfathomable depths of rivers, lakes, and seas also signify a peril that can devour life.
So, in the context we're discussing today,
For instance, we talk about a 'rough patch' or 'getting over a hurdle'.
All of these imply running into danger or facing a tough challenge.
The Hexagram of Zhun signifies that the beginning of all things, their initial stage of creation, is fraught with hardship and peril.
Even for the most colossal giants, any minor disaster or hardship at the very beginning of their sprouting can be utterly devastating.
Let's take an example.
The giant sequoia, the largest single-stem tree on Earth by volume,
Take the famous General Sherman tree, for example.
It stands nearly 84 meters tall, with a trunk volume of about 1,500 cubic meters.
with a girth of over 30 meters at the base.
It would take twenty grown adults to encircle its trunk.
It's estimated to be around 2,200 years old.
The average thickness of its bark is over 60 centimeters.
It can withstand any wildfire or gale-force wind nature throws at it.
So, this is a true titan, seemingly transcending the natural world.
When it first breaks through the soil, it's less than a centimeter tall.
Its stem is as thin as a strand of hair and completely lacks any woody structure.
It has no woody structure whatsoever.
It can barely stand upright, relying solely on the turgor pressure of its cells.
The slightest touch will cause it to bend and snap.
If a gust of wind were to blow, or even a raindrop were to fall at this moment,
Even a single raindrop could be enough to kill it.
Even if you just happened to take a leak on it, you'd kill it.
No matter how incredible a person, thing, or idea is, when it's just born...
are extremely vulnerable in their infancy.
Take Ma Huateng, for example, back when QQ had just launched.
And with their funding about to run out and no one using the product, he then gathered the founders...
So, I had to get the founders together,
They'd pretend to be 'Lan Lan,' 'Xiao Yu,' and 'Wei Wei' to chat with users!
The final line of the hexagram statement is 'It is beneficial to establish a feudal lord.'
The term 'establishing feudal lords,' in its original sense, meant enfeoffing vassals and founding states.
This is extended to mean establishing a foundation.
This means building a framework, establishing order, and attracting talent.
The phrase 'li jian hou' refers to the early stages of creation and inception.
You must first solidify your foundation.
First, establish order.
First, build a small, positive feedback loop.
You need to get your model up and running first.
First, get your cash flow positive, just to survive.
and only then can you start thinking about grand plans for future expansion.
Take the giant sequoia we just talked about, for example.
Now, you're probably wondering,
So, this thing, so fragile in its infancy...
So, how did it manage to survive that dangerous period?
This giant sequoia is the perfect embodiment of the Tun Hexagram!
First off, it makes the absolute most of the right time and place.
It absolutely will not just sprout in any ordinary environment.
Its cones are tightly sealed by resin,
This allows the seeds to be preserved intact on the tree for up to 20 years.
Only the intense heat of a wildfire, over 80 degrees Celsius, can melt the resin and cause the cone to split open.
awakening its seeds.
The reason for this specific condition
is that wildfires can burn away the old layer of dead branches and fallen leaves.
This allows the seeds to make direct contact with the soil.
This prevents the problem of seeds failing to take root.
The wildfire burns away the low shrubs, weeds, and other competing tree species.
With no competitors to block the sunlight or steal water,
The intense heat from the wildfire also wiped out the local rodents.
pest eggs, and pathogenic fungi in the soil.
This dramatically lowers the chances of the seedlings being eaten or infected by disease.
The ash left behind by the wildfire acts as a natural fertilizer and a layer that locks in moisture.
providing nutrients for the seedlings while also acting as a layer of sunscreen.
Have you ever noticed?
Right from the moment a giant sequoia sprouts, it's all about 'do not act rashly'.
It means 'Don't act blindly.'
By the time it does make a move, it has already shielded itself from most fatal risks in advance.
And just how far does this 'favorable to establish a domain' principle go?
A sprout that has just broken through the soil doesn't grow upwards.
It doesn't show off.
It puts all its energy into taking root downward.
In the first three months after it sprouts,
It will dedicate 90% of its energy to growing its root system downwards.
When its above-ground part is only two centimeters tall,
its main taproot has already penetrated 30 centimeters deep into the soil.
By the end of the first year,
the seedling is about 10 centimeters tall.
But its root system has already formed a network one meter in diameter.
Once the roots penetrate into the deeper soil layers,
it's no longer in a state where it would die at the slightest touch.
First off, the sapling on the surface doesn't show its true strength.
So when strong winds blow, there's not much surface area for them to catch.
Even if an accident happens,
as long as the main root is deep enough,
it can still self-recover and stand upright again.
and stand tall once again.
The 'Tuan Zhuan' further elaborates on this state of frenzied root-growth.
The movement of thunder and rain fills the heavens, creating a time of primitive chaos. It is suitable to establish a lord, yet there is no peace.
This means that the thunderstorm is already brewing in the heavens, all set to unleash.
And what follows is a scene of thunderbolts striking, rain pouring down, and the earth thrown into chaos.
In this state, it is "suitable to establish a domain, but there is no tranquility."
It's like having a sword at your throat, leaving you no peace.
The Tuan Zhuan, while emphasizing the need to put down roots and establish a foundation, also stresses the phrase 'and not to be tranquil'.
In other words,
Even if you don't rush ahead or try to expand,
So, while you should 'not act rashly,' you must also be putting down roots.
But you also need to be aware of the risks.
Seize every moment to strengthen your roots and build a solid foundation.
You must not be tempted by a false sense of security.
It's no time to be fooling around.
Working only half a day every day, that's not what being steady means.
That's not what being steady means at all.
It means we should focus all our energy on building our internal strength, not on showing off externally.
not on some bullshit posturing out in the open.
Bullshit! You're not even there yet and you're already trying to make a splash every single day, like, 'I have a dream.'
and just keeps stirring up trouble every single day, sigh...
We must continue to put down roots, in a spirit of unity, vigilance, seriousness, and vitality.
In the early stages of creation, one's foundation is weak.
The threat of catastrophe is ever-present, so we must never let our guard down.
So, let's take a closer look at the judgment of the Hexagram Zhun.
And when we combine this with the stage and core principle of the first line of the Qian Gua, 'A hidden dragon should not be used,'
Does that resonate a little more deeply with you?
So, doesn't the Tun hexagram add some practical guidance for that 'Hidden Dragon' phase?
Now, let's take a look at the progression of each of the six lines in the Zhun hexagram.
The first line, Nine, has the text: 'Wandering, yet firm. It is advantageous to be steadfast, and advantageous to establish a marquis.' The character '磐' (pán) means a massive rock.
And "Huan" refers to a wooden post used as a marker beside ancient postal stations.
Later on, the term was also used to refer to any kind of prominent wooden pillar, like those found at city gates, on bridges, or in temples.
So, when used together, they represent the idea of not acting rashly, but rather taking root firmly, like a massive boulder.
Although the first nine is a yang line in its proper place,
and also the source of all motion.
This perfectly captures the state of all things in their infancy.
But the path ahead is still fraught with peril.
Because your foundation is just too weak.
The moment you stick your head out,
The slightest wind or rain will be enough to snuff it all out.
So, what's the very first thing a seed does after it lands on the ground?
So, what's the very first thing it does after landing?
The vital energy we have at birth isn't meant to be wasted on struggling upwards.
It's not about making sure everyone sees you've arrived.
Instead, it's all about putting all your energy into taking root downwards.
to learn real skills and to grow stronger.
This is the state of "Pan Huan".
In other words, "It is beneficial to be steadfast and beneficial to establish a domain."
First, you need to find the source of your energy, your very foundation.
You need to find your very first stronghold.
This is just like when we're young and first enter the workforce, everyone is full of ambition and grand plans.
Dreaming of achieving great success and making a name for themselves.
But is the first thing we should do at this point really to start our own business from scratch?
Wrong!
First, we need to find a job that can support us and also aligns with our interests.
And pay attention to that 'and'—your interests are usually where your strengths lie.
This will make it easier for you to get more positive feedback for the same amount of effort down the road.
First, we need to make some money to support ourselves.
And then, build up our resource redundancy.
After all, starting a business requires capital.
Even if your startup capital is just your own intelligence and talent,
Don't we also have to cover fixed costs like rent, food, and clothes?
Even if you want to take the same path I did,
I mean, we all started with a job to support the family and shut people up, right?
And look at our second brother, with his narrow vision, writing? What a joke!
At the same time, we need to hone our strengths and define our direction.
So, if you're thinking about starting a business in a certain field down the road,
Then go and learn from the top dog in that field first.
to absorb all the nutrients you can.
until you've mastered every single part of the process.
All of this is what it means to 'build steadily and establish a foundation,' to truly put down roots.
For instance, in China, the company that has produced the most entrepreneurs to date is Tencent.
These "solo-flying penguins" who left Tencent have already founded nearly a thousand companies.
Among them, more than 30 have become unicorn companies.
with a combined market value exceeding 1.5 trillion RMB.
And all these 'flying solo' Tencent alumni inherited a certain gene from their old boss—like pretending to be a girl to chat with users.
and truly grasped what it means to think from the user's perspective.
At Tencent,
Even an ordinary employee could get their hands on products with hundreds of millions of users.
and get involved in everything from product design and tech development to operations and marketing,
all the way to the complete process of monetization.
So, let's master all these skills first before we even think about starting our own business.
At the very least, this approach can help you avoid a lot of unforeseen disasters right from the start.
Just take Tencent's 'Solo Penguins' for example, go ahead and take a look.
They rarely do anything that would disrupt Tencent itself.
Instead, they focus on the gaps within the Tencent ecosystem.
And why's that? Because they know exactly what kind of power the 'King of the Hill' holds!
Now THAT'S what I call being smart!
So many entrepreneurs out there are like, 'Oh man, I'm gonna be the next Alibaba!'
I'm going to be the next Tencent!
What are you even trying to do? You're just asking to get crushed.
That's what you call a complete lack of perspective.
When we're just starting out in the world, just beginning to build something,
The biggest mistake you can make is being impatient.
You always feel like time is your enemy, holding you back from getting rich.
The whole point of studying the I Ching is to fully grasp the patterns and trends that our ancestors have already summarized for us.
So, when we're newcomers entering a new industry,
Your path ahead is definitely going to be full of pitfalls.
Some of these pitfalls are objective,
But of course, most of the pitfalls are subjective.
They're all designed to wipe out newcomers.
And in some industries... well, let's not name names, I don't want to step on any toes.
The money made in these kinds of industries is purely...
It's a bunch of old sharks who've mastered the rules and human nature, preying on the profits of newcomers.
So how are they supposed to make money if the retail investors don't come in?!
The term "panhuan" describes a kind of unwavering stability.
No matter who's tempting us, we just ignore them.
Because you know that when you haven't fully figured out the rules yet,
when you haven't yet seen enough of the potential dangers.
If you go out, you're guaranteed to get taken out.
First, you must take root, and take root firmly.
and absorb the nutrients to sustain yourself, along with the wisdom to build your future foundation.
This is the one and only thing we should be doing right now.
This is the very point supplemented in the 'Tuan Zhuan'.
Although you may be lingering, your will and actions are upright. By humbling yourself in a lowly position, you will greatly win the hearts of the people.
Now, this 'hesitation' doesn't mean you should just stand there like a stone pillar.
It doesn't mean you should just stand there like a stone pillar.
Instead, it's telling you to 'stoop to the humble.'
as a strong, active force, to humble yourself and absorb energy from below.
and put every ounce of effort into establishing a deep and complex root system.
So, when you're a young person who's just entered society and the workforce,
as a young person who's just starting out in the workforce,
Being so down-to-earth and humble,
You'll find that your colleagues will be more than willing to help you out. The veterans will teach you all the tricks of the trade as you help them with their work.
Your older colleagues will see you as this diligent, sweet-talking little brother,
and will have your back, shielding you from any trouble.
And I can speak from personal experience on this.
Over the years at work, the older folks have always treated me like their own son.
The older guys and girls all treated me like their little brother.
No matter which room I went into, they'd always have some snacks for me.
And you know how blessed that makes you feel?
We've used the example of the Mao bamboo many times in our content.
For the first three to four years, the part of the bamboo that grows above ground is only about three centimeters tall.
But underground, its roots are spreading out in every direction, both horizontally and vertically.
laying down a massive network to absorb resources.
But once that foundation is laid, it can grow 30 centimeters a day.
They can grow 30 centimeters a day.
and reach 15 meters in just six weeks.
We should build up a redundancy of our own resources.
technical redundancy, and redundancy in rules and systems.
The more you see through the pitfalls of the industry, the more you stockpile,
The more we have of these reserves,
the clearer we'll see the path we should take in the future.
and how to walk it well.
Or take the I Ching, for instance. It's considered the ancestor of all schools of thought and the source of all principles.
When we first started out in this field, could we have just jumped right in and talked about it?
Of course not.
Because, back then, we hadn't proven ourselves yet.
Why would any audience member be willing to believe you? When we talk about the ancestor of a hundred schools of thought and the source of all principles, what we're really talking about is wisdom.
It's the kind of thinking that comes from applying theory to practice.
It has to be our viewers who've been watching us for many years.
and have seen with their own eyes what we've been saying all these years.
Hey, and that's exactly how this guy did it, step by step.
And after actually making a lot of things happen, step by step,
Only then will you start to believe.
You know, you might actually have some insight into how things work.
Only then can we build a foundation of trust to truly understand the 'I Ching' we're discussing now.
This eight-year, five-million-word journey, from the Partition of Jin to the Chenqiao Mutiny.
From the wisdom of Buddha in Journey to the West, which stems from the fall of Emperor Xiao Yan's dynasty, to the complete interpretation of the classic, revealing the principle of 'returning to the origin' from beginning to end.
It says: 'To linger and hesitate is advantageous for settling, for establishing a lord.'
Now, let's move on to the next stage: the sixth two, a yin line in its correct position and at the center.
In terms of its position, it's arguably the most perfect configuration in the lower trigram.
Alright, let's take a look at the hexagram statement. Heh, it's quite a long one.
The line reads, 'In difficulty, as if on a horse that turns back.' Here, 'difficulty' describes a state of struggling to move forward.
It generally refers to a state of adversity.
Here, the word 'bān' describes a state of circling without making any progress.
This means that the state of the Tun hexagram is like being trapped in confusion, finding it difficult to move forward.
It's like you're on a horse, eager to charge forward,
but you just keep spinning your wheels, going nowhere.
Think back to when you first started your job, or just entered the workforce.
Remember what it was like when you first started out in the real world?
Doesn't it? The character "匪" in "匪寇媾" doesn't mean "bandit" here.
Ah,
It's interchangeable with the character for 'not'. So, what this line means is...
We are like this tender sprout, just breaking through the soil.
We'll encounter people or situations that come and ask us to follow them.
And these people or things don't usually come looking like bandits or robbers.
Instead, they're here to propose to us.
They'll make grand, romantic promises, sweet-talking you with vows to stay together for a lifetime.
Their words are smoother than honey.
promising to spend the rest of their lives with us.
Hey,
Haha, this is the stage where all sorts of powers are trying to trick us into being their pawns.
A woman of integrity does not marry for ten years, and then she does.
The character '字' (zì) here means a woman being of marriageable age.
This is the exact character used in the phrase 'awaiting marriage in the boudoir'.
Now, the 'ten years' here doesn't mean she has to wait until she's an old maid to get married.
Ah.
In numerology, 'ten' represents the end of a cycle.
So, 'ten years' represents a complete, full cycle of time.
So, what this line from the hexagram is saying is that when we first enter the workforce, when we've just started our careers,
Because we're not familiar with the job or the skills it requires,
and we don't know the interpersonal dynamics.
So you feel completely in the dark.
You can't seem to get a handle on anything, and you have no idea which way to go.
and have no idea which way to go.
You're in a state of profound hardship and confusion.
And it's precisely at this moment that all sorts of temptations and enticements will typically come our way.
And they don't come looking like some menacing bandits.
Instead, they come to you under the guise of wanting to build a life together.
They seem to wear their hearts on their sleeves,
Why is that?
We're just a little sprout, just a tiny seedling that's barely begun to grow.
So, what value could you possibly have at this stage?
But of course, it's not like we have none at all, right?
And in some ways, it's actually incredibly valuable.
Our recklessness, our impulsiveness, our raging hormones.
and so on.
Our youthful bodies,
No matter what they're after, they're just using you. It's not like they say, that they're here to propose and marry you for real.
So, what should you do in this situation?
So, hold firm to the 'lingering' of the first nine.
Keep putting down roots, don't be tempted, and don't let yourself be used as a pawn.
and keep focusing on building up your own skills.
As a lady of quality, you have to hold yourself to a higher standard.
You can't just say yes to the first person who comes along proposing.
While we're constantly working on our own value,
and adopt a long-term perspective, one that takes a decade to bear fruit.
Because the entire Hexagram of Zhun is all about that initial, foundational stage of creation.
All this chaos will eventually pass.
The thunder will inevitably pass,
And the clouds will inevitably turn into rain and fall to the ground.
Once the storm has passed, the path forward will become clear.
It won't be too late to make your choice then.
In ancient times, a woman would only get married once.
This is described by the line: 'A woman remains steadfast and does not marry. After ten years, she will marry.'
This also highlights the importance of being extremely cautious in your choices.
It's not that she won't marry,
It's just that when thunder roars and a grim, gloomy mist hangs in the air,
Any opportunity that just comes knocking on your door is probably not a good one.
There are just too many traps waiting inside.
Becoming expendable is one thing, but the real problem is if your reputation gets ruined.
So, what's our next move?
You might even get framed and trapped in a setup.
What kind of future could you possibly have left?
The Xiang Zhuan provides additional commentary on this line: The difficulty of the second six line comes from it being 'ridden' by a firm line. It says, 'ten years to finally have a child'—this is an anomaly.
And the phrase 'ten years to bear a child' signifies a reversal of the natural order.
The term 'riding the firm' refers to a state where a yin line is positioned above a yang line.
The third six is positioned above the first nine.
Although it is in its correct position and central, it is over a strong line.
The Qian and Kun hexagrams are either entirely yang or entirely yin.
So the issue of 'riding the firm' doesn't come into play here.
Starting from the third hexagram, a new condition comes into play.
When the yin is above the yang,
It will naturally be pressured and impacted by the masculine energy below.
This signifies a state where the movement of thunder and rain fills the heavens, creating a time of chaos and new beginnings.
It's a state of chaotic disorder.
You know, it's like the calm before the storm.
This is an anomaly in the objective state of affairs at this moment.
It has nothing to do with us personally.
And this stage corresponds to...
When we are like a tender sprout that has just broken through the soil,
You'll be looked down on, taken advantage of, fed empty promises, and set up for failure.
And the thing is, we haven't actually done anything wrong.
But all sorts of misfortunes will still come our way.
Now, for those of you who haven't been following our content, you're probably having one of two reactions right now.
First, self-doubt and internal conflict.
They'll blame the predicament on something they did wrong.
Second, you become reckless and impulsive, even to the point of panicking and making desperate moves.
They're desperately hoping for some external force to save them from their misery.
You'll go with anyone who comes along and offers a hand.
Remember, at this point, don't get caught up in internal struggles, and even more importantly, don't act on impulse.
This is because 'the difficulty of the second six is that it rides on the firm.'
It's not that we've done anything wrong.
Instead, it's because our position in the ecosystem, being at the Second Six line of the Zhun hexagram, is inherently destined to be a tough one.
This is also the state where you're most vulnerable to weakness and internal conflict.
And then, someone comes along with a so-called 'proposal' for us.
You think he gets you, that he's being completely open and honest with you.
You think it's a 'a man dies for his bosom friend',
But in reality, they're just using you as a cheap, expendable pawn.
You thought they were going to marry you properly,
But in reality, they're just playing you.
This is where the principle of 'ten years to establish, a return to the norm' is needed to guide your path.
Here, the character '反' is a variant of '返', which means 'to return'. So it signifies 'returning to a normal state'.
The phrase 'ten years to establish' means to stay true to your core mission, keep putting down roots, and let things play out over time.
While you're focusing on putting down roots,
and let the bullet fly for a long time.
And just like that, once the chaotic, formative period is over, everything naturally returns to normal.
And everything will return to normal.
By then, you'll see who the real MVP is.
and who's all talk, you'll be able to see clearly.
And by then, you'll have gained enough strength to earn the right to a proper, legitimate union.
and earn the right to be with them openly and properly.
Since ancient times, a lasting partnership has always been about being well-matched!
So, when you're this little newbie and suddenly faced with overwhelming kindness and special treatment...
Now, let that sink in for a moment.
What resources do we have that command a premium price?
If not, what do you think they're trying to get from us?
The Line Statement for the Third Six.
The hexagram text says: 'To chase a deer without a guide is to enter the forest alone.'
A noble person should know when to stop. It is better to let it go than to press on and face regret.
To chase a deer without a guide is to lose your way in the forest.
The original meaning of the character '即' (jì) is 'to eat'.
Because the process of eating involves approaching food.
And so, the character '即' was extended to also mean 'to approach'.
This phrase means to hunt for prey.
but without a gamekeeper familiar with the mountains and forests as a guide.
Ultimately, they can only charge into a perilous and unknown jungle, finding themselves in a dangerous situation.
For the noble person, it is better to let go of an opportunity than to press forward and face humiliation.
Here, the character 'jī' refers to the subtle signs of how things are developing.
As the saying goes, "Ji refers to the subtle signs of change, the early omens of fortune."
danger.
and a precursor to fortune.
So, what this means is,
If you can recognize that 'chasing a deer without a guide' is a dangerous sign,
and by giving up the prey that's run deep into the forest, we can cut our losses.
But if you insist on going in,
then the result will be nothing but hardship and adversity.
Now, 'difficulty' isn't the same as 'blame' or 'misfortune',
But the overall trend is still very unfavorable.
The Xiang Zhuan, or the Commentary on the Images, explains this very well.
A noble person abandons this path, for to proceed leads to hardship and ruin.
You have to resist the temptation and not follow the deer into the woods.
Don't follow the deer into the woods.
If you do go in, the outcome is 'exhaustion'—you'll be trapped with no way out.
The path narrows and narrows until there's nowhere left to go.
The third six is a yin line in a yang position, which is a misplaced position, and it has also lost its centrality.
We've now reached the top of the lower trigram.
This position alone calls for extreme caution.
And the upper trigram is Kan, which represents danger.
Just like a dense forest, it's fraught with danger.
The third six line uses the metaphor of chasing a deer into the forest.
This describes how our young sapling has now reached another layer of temptation.
So, this so-called 'deer' represents all those things that you feel like you could get if you just stretch a little harder.
profits and trends that seem just within your grasp.
Now, there's one thing we need to pay attention to here.
Now, it's not that we're being told not to make a profit or seize opportunities.
Instead, it's asking: do you have a guide? Do you have an insider?
Or to be more precise,
And this 'Yu' isn't just about external help.
授之以鱼不如授之以渔。
It's about whether you yourself have a deep enough understanding of the rules of the industry.
and be fully aware of all the traps lurking deep in the jungle, the ones specifically designed to prey on newcomers.
Let's say, for example,
You know, things like franchise fees and deposits, or promises like, 'Open a store with zero experience, get full support from headquarters, and earn tens of thousands a month!'
and make, like, a gazillion bucks a month!
For instance, let's talk about some pretty funny phenomena that have been popping up recently.
So, 'Business KTV' is a place where you 'discuss K-lines'...
The point being, we must put down roots.
You need to carefully understand the rules of the industry.
and understand the pitfalls set by your peers and colleagues.
Never, ever, when your foundation is still shaky, you're not familiar with the rules, and you lack experience...
and get tempted by the promise of profit.
Now, this isn't to say that the deep woods are always filled with traps set to ensnare you.
There are many,
Oh, absolutely.
The mistakes you could make.
For instance, if from day one of your startup, you don't deeply grasp the life-or-death importance of cash flow...
Then you're bound to fall for some temptation down the line,
and burn through all your reserves, you'll likely face a 'corporate heart attack'.
It's not like all the organs have failed.
It's like you can't even catch your breath before competitors rush in, forcing you out of the market, breaking you, and buying you for pennies on the dollar.
We always encourage the principle of 'actions speak louder than words.'
But that statement isn't entirely correct.
To be more precise,
We always encourage that actions speak louder than words, but only within the bounds of common sense and the rules.
When we're unfamiliar with the rules and have no expert to guide us,
and you have no plan for moving forward or falling back,
and have no surplus resources to fall back on,
No matter how tempting an opportunity may be, you must not take it.
Dark clouds loom, lightning flashes, thunder roars, and a violent wind howls.
In the beginning, when all things are being established,
Beware of reckless ambition that blinds you to the risks.
In fact, even if you've already got one foot caught in the jungle,
In fact, you're still fine at this point. All you have to do is pull back.
A person of virtue simply lets it go.
You must be vigilant.
You have to remind yourself that at this stage, there are no so-called 'great opportunities' to speak of.
That's it.
Don't let the lure of profit lead you blindly into dangerous territory you neither know nor can control.
Have you guys noticed something?
The third and fourth lines of the Zhun Hexagram are all about temptation.
Now, don't you see how profound the wisdom of our ancestors is?
Let's think about ourselves for a second. When we first stepped out into the real world, we thought everything was just so simple, didn't we?
When you first get a little money, you feel like opportunities are everywhere.
Have you ever had that experience where you didn't really know what you were doing, but you just opened an account and jumped right into the stock market?
or the time you just opened an account and jumped right into the stock market?
Have you ever been so fired up by just a few words from someone else?
Our ancestors, through these very hexagrams, were telling us all along: it's all a mirage!
Resist the temptation and put down your roots.
There will be plenty of truly good opportunities in the future.
The prerequisite is that you are worthy of it.
For you, who have just begun to sprout,
It's not yet time to think about those distant things.
Only with tranquility can one achieve far-reaching goals.
Six in the Fourth. Let's look at the line statement.
"Riding a horse, treading warily. It is auspicious to go forward for a marriage proposal. There is nothing unfavorable."
The key here is the character '求' (qiú), which means 'to seek' or 'to pursue'.
In the I Ching, the interaction from a lower line to a higher one is called 'cheng'.
It means 'to hold up with both hands, to carry, to serve.' This state of fulfilling one's proper role is auspicious.
However, if you seek from the bottom up, it's almost always inauspicious.
Because the character 'qiú' doesn't carry the same meaning as the modern word for 'request' or 'seek help', which implies a sense of weakness.
In oracle bone script, the character 'qiú' depicts a whole animal hide with the fur on the outside. Its original meaning is 'qiú', as in the 'qiú' of 'qiú qiān rèn' (a thousand ren of furs).
In ancient times, this was a precious item.
It had to be obtained through hunting, trade, or demanding.
So, its extended meaning, derived from 'acquiring precious things,' is...
It means to take the initiative, to forcibly demand, or to overstep one's bounds in pursuit.
Basically, it's only auspicious to 'seek' from a position of higher authority.
Because only from a higher position can you rightfully seek to acquire.
So, what this line of the hexagram is saying is...
A sprouting seedling halts and hesitates.
After careful consideration,
It should take the initiative to seek out the first nine, the yang line below, to achieve a harmonious union.
Go forth, and it will be auspicious and without disadvantage.
Both the fourth and first lines are positioned at the very bottom of the trigram.
This positional correspondence serves as a reminder for us of the embryonic stage at the very beginning of any venture.
Even when you've already entered the later stages,
We've now reached the fourth line, Six-Four.
The best course of action is still to return to the original intent of the First Nine.
Remember what the first nine was all about?
To hesitate and take root, to be steadfast and establish a foundation.
Keep putting down roots and building your foundation.
and to hone your own skills.
The line from the 'Xiang Zhuan' commentary, 'To seek and then to go is to be enlightened,' is the perfect finishing touch.
This is why the action taken by the fourth six line to seek the first nine line is considered wise.
This is because the hexagram statement for the entire Zhun Hexagram reads: 'Supreme success, perseverance. It is not favorable to go forth. It is favorable to establish feudal lords.'
and it is beneficial to establish a domain.
There are both grand principles and minor principles in all matters.
And all these smaller principles are governed by the greater one.
Always remember that this hexagram, as a whole, is perilous.
This requires caution.
Taking root and establishing a solid foundation is an absolute must.
You must have self-awareness.
The self-awareness in the Zhun hexagram is about recognizing your own weakness.
The outside world is unpredictable; the only safe path is to put down roots.
Striving for the top is perilous.
This holds true even when you reach the next line, the Ninth Five, which represents the position of a ruler.
Even when it's in the right position and well-balanced,
it still can't be considered entirely auspicious.
The fifth nine: 'Amassing its resources. For a small matter, correctness brings good fortune. For a great matter, correctness brings misfortune.'
So, this character '屯' is not pronounced as 'zhūn' here.
It means to hoard or to stockpile.
The line '屯其膏' (tún qí gāo) means that at this point, after putting down deep roots, we have already gathered some resources.
We've built up some resources.
At this point, you can gradually and progressively move forward, but only on the premise of having a solid foundation.
to start taking on some small tasks and experiments.
This is a small but favorable step.
Because you've already gained some experience and have a buffer to fall back on.
Now, you can start experimenting on a small scale.
So, at this stage, any small action you take is auspicious, regardless of whether it succeeds or fails.
Even if these small experiments fail, they are still valuable lessons.
Because the scale is small, we can handle the consequences.
This is also an essential part of moving beyond the initial, budding stage.
But if you go for a massive expansion,
and try to achieve some grand success,
you will inevitably court disaster.
The word 'misfortune' that appears in this line statement,
It represents the worst possible outcome in all of the I Ching's divinations.
You absolutely cannot take this lightly.
The reason why taking major action is doomed to bring disaster is this:
I mean, at this point, you're just a tiny sprout. How much of a foundation could you possibly have?
And...
It's also a reminder of the objective reality of the situation.
but your actions and your strategies still won't lead to a bright future.
Even though the fifth nine is the supreme sovereign line,
you are still bound by the principles of this hexagram.
The Ninth-Five line in the Qian Gua and the Ninth-Five line in the Tun Gua are two completely different concepts.
It's like the difference between a king and a class monitor.
Overall, the Tun hexagram represents the initial stage of sprouting, which is fraught with peril.
So, for these minor situations, you can't really say that a solid line in the ruler's position is always a sign of great fortune.
The fifth nine line of the Zhun hexagram also defines the boundaries of action and the ironclad rules for success or failure in the initial stages of any endeavor.
In the beginning, you must respect the boundaries of that beginning.
We must revere the objective law of the initial hardships all things face at their inception.
Without this reverence, one can never move beyond the Hexagram of Zhun.
Instead, you've reached the dead end of the Zhun hexagram.
We're now at the final line.
Although the top sixth line is a yin line in a yin position, which means it is in its proper place,
However, it is over a firm line, the Nine in the Fifth.
It also loses its centrality, positioned at the very peak of the perilous pit.
And all of this is within the broader framework of the Zhun hexagram.
So, it's doomed to end badly.
It says, "Riding a horse, hesitant and uncertain; weeping tears of blood, in a continuous stream."
This means that
If you insist on acting the moment you get some resources,
and just a little bit of slack,
and go all-in just when you're starting to figure things out,
Then you'll quickly find out
You'll find yourself back at square one, lost and going in circles before you've even taken a few steps.
But the "hesitation on horseback" at this stage is a whole different story compared to the ones in the sixth two and sixth four lines.
When you were hesitating with your horse in the second and fourth lines, you still had some room to maneuver.
But when we get to the top sixth line, it's a real shame.
At this point, going in circles is a sign of extreme grief and regret, so profound it's like weeping tears of blood.
It's not just shedding tears anymore; it's crying blood.
And the word '涟如' (lián rú) describes these tears of blood—they're not just dripping down.
It means they're streaming down, one after another, endlessly.
This line really drives home the sheer depth of your regret after being too greedy and rushing ahead in the Zhun hexagram.
This is actually one of the rarest kinds of hexagrams in the I Ching.
It's an omen of great misfortune with absolutely no room for maneuver!
And this line from the Xiang Zhuan, 'To weep blood, how can this last?' is like twisting the knife.
You're already weeping tears of blood.
Don't be fooled just because you're still on your horse,徘徊着.
But soon enough, you won't even have that horse anymore.
You're about to hit a dead end.
Doesn't that sound like what happens after you've scrimped and saved for ten years, only to pour it all into some... you-know-what?
Doesn't that sound like right after you've finally started to get somewhere,
You take out loans to massively hire people, bring in new equipment to scale up production, and then...
and then the orders suddenly just stop coming in?
Isn't the wisdom of our ancestors just incredible?
So, the question is, can wisdom from thousands of years ago still be applied today?
So, for this hexagram,
Finally, let's revisit the profound meaning of the entire Hexagram of Zhun.
Supreme success. Perseverance furthers. Do not act. It furthers one to build up feudal lords.
Step one: focus on building a solid foundation and learning real skills.
Study past failures to identify the major pitfalls in your industry.
Step two: Don't get caught up in internal struggles, and don't be tempted by distractions.
Ground yourself and repeat the first step.
Step two: don't make any rash moves.
Even if you achieve some small success in the first step, you must still test the waters with small-scale actions.
Any major move is a death sentence.
So, what's the next step?
It is education.
It's about helping all things, in their earliest stages of growth, to understand the fundamental laws of how things develop.
to understand the fundamental laws of heaven and earth.
And this brings us to the Hexagram of Meng.
Let's take a look at the fundamental principles in the process of education and learning.
Aren't you always getting frustrated that you just can't seem to raise this kid right?!
And aren't you always wondering why you can never stick with anything you try to learn?
and why you never seem to get anywhere with your own studies.
And you just can't seem to get the hang of anything, right?
Well, come on! Our ancestors have already summed it all up for us!
Everything that has just sprouted, all newborn things, are completely in the dark.
They know absolutely nothing.
We usually call this state of being 'ignorance' or 'obscurity'.
Regarding this concept of 'Meng' (Ignorance), as recorded in the 'Shuowen Jiezi'...
“Meng, the royal maiden.”
Now, this 'wang nu' doesn't mean 'princess,' by the way.
It refers to dodder.
This thing works by wrapping itself around a host plant,
piercing the host's epidermis to absorb nutrients.
So, in the vast majority of ancient texts,
Originally, the character "Meng" meant to be covered or obscured.
And because it's covered up, we can't see clearly.
And so, the character 'Meng' also came to mean 'to be deceived' or 'to be blinded'.
And because people who are deceived also have their judgment impaired,
And so, the character 'Meng' also came to mean the 'ignorance' or 'naivety' we just talked about.
But when it comes to the character 'Meng'...
But our ancestors didn't mean this in a derogatory way at all.
"Meng" is an inevitable stage at the very beginning of any development.
This is what the 'Sequence of the Hexagrams' says:
“All things that are born must be in a state of obscurity. Therefore, it is followed by Meng.”
Meng means to be in a state of ignorance; it is the infancy of all things.
It means being tender, being young, being a child.
The Meng Hexagram is Gen above, and Kan below.
Gen represents the mountain, which means to stop. Kan represents water, which means danger.
Kan represents water, and water represents danger.
The lower trigram begins with the peril of Kan.
Danger.
This tells us to be careful.
After passing through the lower trigram, we reach the upper trigram, which is another mountain.
telling us to stop.
The Tuan Zhuan states, "Beneath the mountain lies danger, and one halts in the face of danger."
Beneath the mountain, danger is lurking.
This describes a path forward that's blocked by danger.
This state of obscured peril, hidden by the mountain,
It's a state of being like a child, knowing nothing at all.
When the path ahead is unclear and your understanding is limited,
Just how terrifying is this world for us, fresh out of the tutorial?
So, what does this mean?
This calls for education that disciplines children and prunes young trees.
Failing to educate them is doing them a great disservice.
In other words, to initiate their education.
Alright, let's take a look at the judgment for this hexagram.
It is prosperous. It is not I who seek the childlike, but the childlike who seeks me.
Things go wrong.
For the first divination, it gives an answer. But if you ask again and again, it will not answer, for it is treated with disrespect.
Favorable to be steadfast.
First, let's pay attention. The hexagram statement contains the words 'heng' (prosperity), 'li' (benefit), and 'zhen' (steadfastness).
But the 'Yuan' is missing.
This tells us that...
When it comes to education and enlightenment,
It's not something we are inherently and automatically entitled to the moment we are born.
Education and wisdom are luxuries.
Not everyone gets the chance or is even qualified to obtain it.
That's why we must cherish the opportunity to 'seek knowledge'.
亨。匪我求童蒙，童蒙求我。
The essence of enlightenment is 'smooth progress'.
It's about helping the audience see through the fog.
to ensure your heart and your path can flow with clarity and ease.
Now, there's one point we need to emphasize here.
The concept of 'Heng', or smooth progress, is actually something that's highly customized and varies from person to person.
This is the path for those with Jia and Yi Wood elements.
it might not be the right path for those with Bing or Ding.
People with strong 'Shi Shang' and those with heavy 'Guan Sha'
These represent two completely different life strategies.
It would be like asking Liu Bang to be Xiao He; you're just setting him up to fail.
He just loved to piss on the hats of Confucian scholars.
or forcing his son-in-law to do the splits and flash his junk.
or splitting open his opponent's crotch.
You'd have Xiao He hold the line at Xingyang and Chenggao against Xiang Yu's bombardment,
But if you let the theorists like Zhang Liang and Chen Ping
to command those old, tough founding fathers.
And they just don't have that kind of authority to command respect.
This kind of job calls for someone with that special 'He Wanqian' quality.
Only a protagonist with the right temperament can pull it off.
So, when it comes to启蒙 (enlightenment), it all starts from the very beginning.
This is why we have to emphasize tailoring the teaching to the individual.
There's no single formula that can be applied to everyone.
And this goes back to what we said at the very beginning.
The Meng Hexagram does not have the 'Yuan' quality.
Nor does it mean that every single child needs to be educated.
that they are all destined to receive an education.
From the very beginning, the Meng Hexagram serves as a reminder for all those who are teachers, or who are eager to teach others.
You don't have to force the issue of school on your kids.
And it's not a given that you'll be able to get through to them.
The purpose of studying the I Ching is to help us understand the Way of Heaven.
and realize that not everyone can be educated.
is to know that true wisdom is costly.
It is a solemn matter.
and that it must be treated with reverence. This is the very prerequisite for true enlightenment.
“Difficult! Difficult! Difficult!”
The Tao is the most profound mystery.
Do not treat the Golden Elixir as a trivial matter.
Without a true master to impart the secret, all your empty words will just wear out your tongue and leave you dry!
Let's go over that one more time.
Understand that not everyone can be taught.
To understand that true knowledge is a precious and solemn thing...
and that it must be treated with reverence. This is the prerequisite for true enlightenment.
The moment you truly grasp this, your whole world will suddenly expand.
Some kids, or even most of them, actually just don't have what it takes.
And it's even more unnecessary to forcibly interfere with other people's karma. If they have the right stuff, they'll have that blessing.
They would naturally cross two vast oceans to seek the Way.
So naturally, no matter how you try to tempt them,
One moment it's the principle of stillness, the next it's the principle of action.
He remained steadfast in his pursuit of immortality.
It's like, even if you hit him, he'd probably think you're just telling him the time.
He'd even think you're just giving him a massage.
The teachers, the ones who impart wisdom, are the ones who test you from beginning to end.
We shouldn't be the one to rush things. That's not how the natural order works.
“It is not I who seek the naive, but the naive who seek me.”
The unenlightened seek me, this 'un' is not 'together' or 'same'.
This echoes the line from the second six line of the previous hexagram, 'Halted, entangled, riding in a team of horses.'
as if they were bandits.
The word '匪' (fěi) in the line '匪寇婚媾女子貞不字十年乃字' (fěi kòu hūn gòu, nǚ zǐ zhēn bù zì, shí nián nǎi zì)
and after ten years, she finally bears a child.
So, the character 'fei' here has the same meaning.
So, what this means is...
It's not about the teacher rushing after the students, begging them to come and learn from them.
It's the children who must come to the teacher, sincerely seeking knowledge.
This is the prerequisite for education.
The student's initiative is the prerequisite for any education to be effective.
no matter how high our level of启蒙 (qǐméng) is,
But if the person being taught has no desire to learn at all,
That would be treating the Golden Elixir as something trivial.
The Tuan Zhuan, or the Commentary on the Decision, provides the following commentary on this passage.
Meng is prosperous. By acting in accordance with the time, one attains centrality.
It is not I who seek the young and ignorant; it is the young and ignorant who seek me. This is because our wills are in accord.
The student seeks me out, and our wills align.
“To act by offering” means to act in accordance with the momentum.
To be 'timely and centered' means avoiding extremes and not forcing things.
and not to force-feed knowledge.
“Zhi Ying” means having a shared purpose, being on the same wavelength as your teacher.
For those who are just starting out, we must teach them according to their aptitude and go with the flow.
This kid just isn't cut out for it.
Then don't force it. But what if the kid is talented, but right now, all they can think about is having fun?
but all they can think about is having fun,
and they don't even respect you, then just leave them be.
But what if the kid isn't naturally gifted, yet their heart is completely in it?
Then teach them the basic principles for living a stable and grounded life.
The guiding principle of an educator is to teach according to the student's aptitude and to discern the right moment.
Teach when it's time to teach.
and hold back when necessary.
When you come across a devout student,
regardless of their aptitude,
One must sincerely impart the knowledge and skills that are right for them.
But at best, we're just the coaches.
But when it's game time, the athletes have to be the ones on the field.
We neither understep nor overstep our bounds.
The principles have been explained, and the knowledge has been taught.
If you run into any problems, you can come to me for advice.
and I can offer you some guidance.
But, I'm sorry to say, when it comes to your own life, you have to walk that path by yourself.
For those who seek to learn, there's one crucial mindset you must always remember.
Let go of our arrogance.
If you're going to ask for guidance, you should act like it.
Once we've acquired knowledge and wisdom,
is what can change our destiny.
Therefore, you must develop a genuine sense of respect for your mentor from the bottom of your heart.
At the same time, it's not just the mentor who matters; the student is just as important.
must also observe the principle of 'acting with sincerity'.
So, you need to go with the flow and build a connection with your mentor.
The energy and time of highly accomplished people are incredibly precious.
So, what's in it for them to teach you?
Why on earth would they just hand over the secrets they've spent decades of blood, sweat, and tears figuring out?
and reveal all their secrets to you?
We should learn from the Monkey King.
He traveled across two great oceans in search of his own scriptures.
It would take him six or seven years, alongside his fellow disciples, to learn the proper etiquette, discuss scriptures and doctrines, practice calligraphy, and burn incense. This was his daily routine.
In his spare time, he would sweep the floors, tend to the garden, care for the flowers and trees, and gather firewood to light the fires.
Only after carrying water and hauling mortar could he finally await his chance.
the opportunity for the Patriarch to ascend the dais, summon all the immortals, and expound upon the Great Dao.
Only through sufficient hardship and unwavering sincerity,
and enough sincerity,
Only then can you truly understand what it is you want.
Only then can you face the various interferences from the 'Masters,' such as the 'School of Technique,' the 'School of Stillness,' and the 'School of Action.'
the Mirror Gate,
and the distractions from the 'Action' school.
He still refused to learn.
I want to learn the art of immortality.
This was the 'secret signal'—the Patriarch striking him three times.
And then, he finally unraveled the mystery of the plate.
As we've mentioned when discussing 'Journey to the West'...
In the beginning, Monkey King was actually the most polite monkey in the world.
He was practically exuding an aura of Buddhist wisdom.
It was only in this state of mind that he was able to master the Great Pinnacle Heavenly Immortal Art.
So, once he got his skills down and started running his mouth all the time, did he get any better?
Not at all! He was already getting stewed in a pot.
And he still dared to mess with the Buddha!
It wasn't until he was crushed under that mountain for 500 years that he learned there's always someone better out there.
Only when the Golden Fillet was placed on his head, could his very life and death be controlled at another's whim.
It wasn't until he was cast out by Tang Sanzang at White Tiger Ridge and lost his chance to change his fate,
and lost his chance to change his fate,
Only then did he gradually let go of his arrogance and develop a sincere heart.
Only then did his wisdom regain the high ground.
Only by persevering to the end could he truly complete the latter half of his pilgrimage.
and turned it into his own path of spiritual cultivation.
All of Monkey King's upgrades on his path to enlightenment were rooted in his sense of reverence.
and only initiated after securing a strategic high ground once again.
The first divination gives an answer. If you ask again and again, it is disrespectful and will not be answered. It is beneficial to be steadfast.
Here, 'divination' refers to the practice of fortune-telling. When you sincerely consult the oracle for the first time,
the divination should如实 reveal the result.
But if you ask over and over again,
and won't stop until they get the answer they want,
Or, even after you've given them the answer, they refuse to believe it.
That is a sign of disrespect.
This is a blasphemy against the divine. And once blasphemed, no more will be revealed.
Here, the rules of divination are used as a metaphor for the boundaries of education.
This is when a seeker first earnestly asks for guidance,
And pay attention here: it must be sincere.
The mentor should impart true knowledge as it is.
At this point, the learner should take the teaching to heart and reflect on it deeply.
Practice it repeatedly until it becomes second nature, integrated into your own operating system.
If someone asks the same question, or questions about the same kind of matter, over and over again,
he doesn't reflect on it,
This would be a sign of disrespect and contempt.
then the teacher should not tell them.
So, the key here is 'sincerity', alright?
It's not like you just answer every random question that comes along, you know?
It was the Monkey King who proved his sincerity.
He's already come at the third watch of the night.
The Patriarch should now teach him the Great Pinnacle Heavenly Immortal Art.
And it's not like the guy wasn't sincere enough.
He's already solved the riddle of the plate, going to all this trouble to come at the third watch of the night.
And then you just come back with a bunch of empty words.
This principle of 'disrespect brings no answer' is not about the teacher being cold or giving up.
It's not that they're not giving you a chance,
Because the true knowledge was already given to you from the very beginning.
It's not that the teacher isn't dedicated.
The problem is you didn't take it seriously.
So, you might be wondering, what if the student is just plain dumb?
So, what if the student is just hopelessly stupid?
As we mentioned earlier, the Meng Hexagram lacks the 'Yuan' quality.
It was never meant for everyone to attain enlightenment in the first place.
But what if you've explained it clearly, and they still don't get it?
That just means the time isn't right yet. You need to let it simmer for a while longer, wait for the moment to be ripe.
So, if it's not a matter of the student being stupid,
Then it's a matter of mindset.
Or, they don't take the teacher seriously.
or they take the Golden Elixir for granted.
Or, they take themselves way too seriously.
Their minds are so full of their own ideas and obsessions that there's no room for anything else.
This is something the learner must reflect on for themselves.
If he's just not cut out for it, and you keep trying to teach him over and over again,
they'll just get rebellious.
If they don't take you seriously, but you keep trying to teach them,
On one hand, you're letting down the masters who came before you.
Heaven, Earth, and even the spirits will see that you have failed to uphold the dignity of a teacher!
On the other hand, you're actually ruining him and doing him harm.
and encourage his disrespectful and impetuous tendencies.
The Commentary on the Decision, or Tuan Zhuan, explains this line as: 'The first divination gives an answer.'
Because they possess the virtue of firmness and centrality.
If you ask a second time, it shows disrespect. And if you disrespect it, you will not be answered. This is what it means to abuse the spirit of seeking guidance.
The reason you should sincerely answer someone who sincerely seeks your guidance for the first time,
This is because the teacher embodies the virtue of being 'firm and centered'.
The second line of this hexagram is a solid, or yang, line.
The second line, Nine, is a firm line in a central position.
This means that, on one hand, the educator must have a firm, unyielding principle.
and on the other hand, they must have a sincere heart of integrity and peace to educate others with the Way.
This is what it means to be a qualified guide for the unenlightened.
“If you repeatedly show disrespect, I will not answer. This is what it means to disrespect the unenlightened.”
In fact, this means that the ignorant are not just disrespecting their teachers and true knowledge.
but more so, with distracting thoughts of utilitarianism, arrogance, and impetuousness.
but are also desecrating their own innermost being.
and has shut the door to enlightenment.
He has even failed himself.
At this point, the problem lies with the one seeking guidance, not with the one imparting it.
The teacher's refusal to answer is meant to prompt the student to reflect on their own shortcomings.
First, find your true self.
First, know your place, then we can talk about enlightenment.
“If you show disrespect, you will not be told.”
It is the 'teaching without words' of the Great Way.
So, do you understand the principle behind why you shouldn't be so eager to lecture others?
After all these years, I believe we've all learned to keep our mouths shut.
We've learned not to interfere with the law of cause and effect.
But in fact, our ancestors had already summed it all up for us long ago.
Of course, for those who haven't been through the wringer,
Even if they see this, they won't truly grasp its meaning.
and they won't take it seriously.
But when you do take a fall,
Only when reality connects with the theory,
That's when this principle will be truly etched into your very being.
This is, in fact, a reflection of the principle: 'It is not I who seek the ignorant child, but the ignorant child who seeks me.'
This is the manifestation of 'the student seeking the teacher.'
The Great Way is right there.
Once you've sailed through a thousand ports and realized that the greatest truths are the simplest,
The time has come to revere the wisdom of our ancestors.
Only then can you truly begin to level up.
The last two characters of the Judgment for the Meng Hexagram are "li zhen".
This reiterates the foundation of the Meng Hexagram.
The word 'beneficial' implies that for both the teacher and the learner,
Both parties should gain their fair and reasonable benefits.
The true knowledge and skills imparted by the teacher
must be something that empowers the learner to stand on their own two feet for the rest of their life.
Otherwise, you're just leading them astray!
This carries great karmic weight! And the one seeking guidance must also prepare the solemn "Six Rites of Shuxiu" for the teacher.
to express your sincerity and righteous intentions.
All that empty talk and flashy stuff won't get you anywhere.
The world has always been a pragmatic place, since ancient times.
This was especially true in ancient times.
You only cherish what you've earned through effort.
The character 'Zhēn' signifies that the core of all teaching and learning revolves around the right path.
The fundamental purpose of education is to guide the learner onto the right path.
This is exactly what the Tuan Zhuan says: "To nourish the young with correctness is the work of the sages."
Tailoring education to individual aptitude means providing positive guidance for each person.
and to empower them to have a positive impact on the world.
The most fundamental purpose of education has never been the mere imparting of knowledge.
but the cultivation of virtue.
That's what the Sweeper Monk said.
The greater one's martial arts prowess, the greater the destructive energy it can unleash.
the more it needs the compassionate Dharma to neutralize it.
Regardless of whether this child succeeds in their studies or not,
regardless of their abilities,
At the very least, after this child has received their early education,
he or she should at least be a person who is not a harm to society.
For those who are immoral and violent, the first step is to cultivate their character.
Otherwise, you'd just be irresponsible to society!
This is precisely the summary of the entire hexagram found in the 'Great Image Commentary'.
Meng: A spring emerging from beneath a mountain.
A noble person cultivates virtue through resolute action.
Let's look at the line statement for the first six, "To initiate the unenlightened, it is beneficial to use the punished to break the shackles."
This means that the starting point of enlightenment is to establish rules, clarify boundaries, and rectify discipline.
In the Meng Hexagram, the first six is a yin line in a yang position, which is considered out of place.
This means it is in a yang position, but it is not a proper fit.
The soft and yielding is in the lowest position, representing the utmost ignorance.
Therefore, at this stage, this state of 'Meng' needs to be 'initiated' or 'enlightened'.
This requires help from an external force.
You can't count on some kind of spontaneous, natural awakening.
It requires external guidance.
Now, the word 'xing' in the phrase 'utilizing punitive measures'...
Now, this doesn't mean just meting out punishment or corporal punishment, okay?
Instead, it refers to establishing rules, like the principle of 'cultivating virtue before martial arts'.
When those being taught clearly violate the rules, or even the law,
appropriate punishment must be meted out.
The explanation in the Xiang Zhuan is quite apt.
“Employing punishment is for the sake of upholding the law.”
Punishment is not about inflicting violence.
It is to uphold justice, to establish clear boundaries.
to establish a righteous system of values.
This is the fundamental principle of enlightenment.
"to cast off the fetters"
Here, the character '说' (shuō) is interchangeable with '脱' (tuō), which means 'to take off'. '桎梏' (zhì gù) refers to ancient instruments of punishment, like shackles.
Finally, it is said, 'set the will.'
The first principle is 'solidity'.
So, the complete meaning of this line of the hexagram is: to enlighten the ignorant.
It's about instilling a sense of reverence in those who seek guidance from the very beginning.
and understand the boundaries.
This is the only way to help them later on, to break free from the shackles of their minds and their bad habits.
When a person is first born,
So, what do you think? Are people inherently good, or are they inherently evil?
The idea of innate goodness is correct, and the idea of innate evil is also correct.
The idea that human nature is inherently good means that at the very beginning,
They don't have the capacity to commit sins like killing, stealing, sexual misconduct, lying, or drinking.
The idea that human nature is evil, on the other hand, holds that at the very beginning, we are already full of greed, anger, ignorance, arrogance, and doubt.
This one point is so spot-on, anyone who's raised a child knows exactly what I'm talking about.
At the very beginning of a child's life,
They are completely and utterly driven by patterns of extreme selfishness and self-interest.
And so, the purpose of our education is to teach the ignorant the objective laws of this world.
We teach them to stay away from fire and water, and to know what they can and can't eat.
and to greet your elders when you see them.
Don't take things that aren't yours, and so on and so forth.
If they fail to grasp these fundamental rules,
let alone make a place for themselves in society.
they won't even be able to survive.
So, the very first lesson in启蒙, or启蒙, is to teach children what the absolute taboos are.
Many mistakes, once made, mean you'll have to start all over again in the next life.
So, why do people observe a three-year mourning period for their parents after they die?
In reality, it's 27 months.
This is because, as the saying goes, 'A child is not free from the embrace of its parents until three years of age.'
Before a child reaches the age of three,
In fact, every single day is a life-or-death struggle.
The moment you look away, they could fall into a well.
If you don't feed them for two days, they'll starve to death.
It's just that their parents have kept them alive for the first three years, that's all.
So, what's the state of a young child?
Cute as they may be,
But their minds are still undeveloped, they can't tell right from wrong, and they act on their every whim.
This is where the educator comes in, to set rules, define boundaries, and establish consequences.
Setting clear boundaries is a form of discipline.
To put it in terms of a lot of trendy educational methods today,
This is what's called 'gentle firmness.' You make the boundaries clear to them. Rules are rules.
You just can't cross the line. If you do, you will be punished.
Either a spanking on the butt, or standing in the corner.
Without rules, there's no order!
Without discipline, there can be no enlightenment!
The final part of this line, "to go will bring hardship"...
Here, "to go" means to take the initiative, to step beyond the boundaries.
And 'ke' signifies hardship, regret, and adversity.
This is talking about the taboos during the initial, formative stage.
Don't rush for quick results, and don't ignore the rules.
In the early stages of establishing rules and nurturing the mind, don't try to force growth.
Let children grow at their own pace. Don't rush them to succeed.
The key at this stage is not to overlook those seemingly 'minor' misbehaviors in your child.
Because, as the saying goes, 'Treading on frost, the solid ice will come.'
Setting these rules now is all about laying a solid foundation for the future.
So, to sum it all up, the first thing in启蒙 is...
is about setting rules, not just imparting knowledge.
Slow and steady growth is better than forced progress.
The second nine, "Nourishing the Ignorant, auspicious." This "nourishing the ignorant" refers to dealing with all kinds of ignorance.
An educator must possess an inclusive and tolerant character, teaching all without discrimination.
and not see them through a biased lens.
and tailors the teaching to each sincere student according to their aptitude.
This is the righteous virtue of the teaching path.
Those whose virtue matches their position are destined to find good fortune.
This is just like how a doctor's sacred duty is to heal the sick and save lives.
Whether this person is a good guy or a bad guy is not for the healer to consider.
As long as they seek knowledge with a sincere heart, the teacher should impart it.
But what to teach, and how, requires the teacher to tailor their instruction to the individual student.
But what if a bad person sincerely comes to learn?
Then they should be taught as well.
However, the first priority is to cultivate virtue.
As long as they are sincere, a teacher must be tolerant and nurturing.
To guide and transform, and to accept one's duties.
The line 'Taking a wife brings good fortune' means that by marrying and uniting the masculine and feminine, one is certain to achieve auspiciousness.
As we've mentioned, the second and fifth lines are in the middle positions, serving as a bridge connecting the top and bottom.
They are the core pivot.
So, these two positions are generally considered favorable, regardless of whether they are yin or yang.
In the Meng Hexagram, the second line is a Yang line in a Yin position. Although it is not in its proper place, it is located in the central position of the lower trigram, which means the Yang line has attained centrality.
But it is positioned in the middle of the lower trigram.
When a yang line is centered, it is also called 'firmly centered'.
Here, taking a wife is used as a metaphor for the 'firm and central' virtue of the Nine in the Second Place.
The term "taking a wife" refers to the Nine in the Second Place coming to marry the Six in the Fifth Place, its corresponding partner, which we will discuss later.
The second line, Nine, is a yang line in a yin position.
The sixth five is a yin line in a yang position.
Let's talk about the line statement for the sixth five in advance.
In other words, the 'naive student' seeks out the 'enveloping mentor,' which corresponds to that specific line in the hexagram's commentary.
It is not I who seek the young and ignorant, but the young and ignorant who seek me.
Now, the "childlike seeker" here is the sixth five line. And even though it holds the position of a ruler,
But it still has to humble itself and proactively reach down to the Ninth Two.
and take the initiative to seek out the Nine in the Second Place.
It's like, even if you're a prince,
you still have to show your teacher the proper respect and perform the rites due to a master.
As the saying goes, "Only when the teacher is respected, can the Way be esteemed."
Only when the Way is respected will the people know to honor learning.
“There are two cases in which a ruler does not treat his subjects as subjects.”
“When he is a teacher, he is not to be treated as a subject.”
The rites of the great learning state that even when a teacher is summoned by the Son of Heaven, he does not face north.
Even if the Son of Heaven himself is present, the master does not face north.
And that's why teachers are held in such high regard. See? Since ancient times, the rule has been that even the Son of Heaven, when facing his teacher...
the teacher is also exempt from the kneeling rites between a ruler and his subject.
Instead, the Son of Heaven must perform a formal bow as a student to his teacher.
The dignity of the master-student relationship transcends the hierarchy between a ruler and his subject!
Let's make a comparison, shall we? Even when the Empress meets her own father,
Even the Empress's father must perform the kneeling ceremony to his own daughter, as a subject to his sovereign.
Because since ancient times, the bond between a ruler and his subject has always preceded that of a father and his son.
But the Emperor's Tutor is an exception, because the way of the teacher transcends the relationship between a ruler and his subject!
And this has been the way of things in our Chinese civilization since ancient times.
Starting from the Qin and Han dynasties, the etiquette for princes towards their tutors was codified into law.
And this tradition was reinforced with each passing generation.
By the time of the Qing Dynasty,
They even incorporated the princes' respect for their teachers into the imperial family's code of conduct.
And its enforcement was the strictest of any dynasty in history.
Throughout the entire Qing Dynasty, there was hardly a single prince who dared to slack off or show disrespect to their tutors.
Anyone who violated these rules would face severe punishment from the emperor.
Since ancient times, their studies have always centered on the Four Books and Five Classics.
So, the imperial family clearly understood what the Meng Hexagram was all about.
No matter how big a shot you are, you have to humble yourself when you seek knowledge.
Only with this kind of attitude can you truly achieve success in your studies!
Now, if we take a closer look at the imagery of the Meng Hexagram, which is 'Mountain over Water,' it shows the mountain in the upper trigram seeking out the water in the lower trigram.
This once again reflects the degree of their devotion.
The lower trigram of this hexagram represents the one who teaches.
The upper trigram represents the one seeking knowledge. It should ascend to approach the lower, just as the yin approaches the yang.
This is precisely what the final line of the Yao text means by 'a son who can manage the household'.
The character 'Ke' here doesn't mean 'to overcome' or 'to conquer'.
It means to be capable and to take on responsibilities.
or 'pay-to-win'.
It's the same 'ke' as in 'diligent and frugal.' It refers to a child who approaches learning with a devout and humble attitude.
Only then can they become pillars of the community.
and only then can they shoulder great responsibilities in the future.
This line from the 'Xiang Zhuan', 'The son can manage the family, because the strong and the gentle are in contact,'
The Xiang Commentary further elaborates on this, explaining the interaction between the firm and the yielding.
First, as we mentioned earlier, the Nine in the Second Place, despite its low position...
But it still requires the humble and noble you, the Six in the Fifth, to come down.
And don't be fooled by the lowly position of the Nine in the Second Place.
But the thing is, it's a Yang line.
Even when you, the fifth six, arrive, they will still have to 'enlighten the ignorant by applying penalties, using shackles and fetters.'
He'll use masculine, righteous principles to set the rules for you.
The high submits to the low, the yin follows the yang.
No matter how high your status or how wealthy your family is,
even a son,
must also cast aside these external things.
and approach your studies with the utmost humility.
If even students of high status are like this,
let alone children from ordinary families.
So what right do we have to look down on our teachers?
The lowly do not fear the high, and the strong do not fawn upon the weak.
This is the dignity and integrity that educators must uphold.
If you don't respect me,
or if you don't follow the rules I've set,
It doesn't matter how high your status is, or how much money you offer me.
I will not take you as my student.
Because leniency in teaching is the teacher's dereliction of duty. Indulging you is actually harming you.
We can't bear the karma of leading our students astray.
No matter how humble your background, as long as you come to learn with a sincere heart,
and show the utmost respect your family can afford.
Then that's what we call fate.
And in turn, we will impart to you all the knowledge we have, based on the materials you provide.
To all our dear seekers of knowledge and mentors,
So, does this offer any inspiration for you and your own 'treasures'?
Now, let's look at the third six.
The line statement says, 'It is not advantageous to take a wife who has seen a man of wealth.'
Disregard for one's own integrity brings no advantage.
A yin line in a yang position is out of place, and it's also off-center.
Furthermore, it resides at the zenith of the Kan trigram, which represents danger, pitfalls, and confusion.
This line of the hexagram also represents the peak of danger.
This line begins with the stark warning: 'Do not take this woman.'
Now, the character '取' (qǔ) here is a pun for '娶' (qǔ), which means 'to marry' as in 'marrying a wife'.
It starts right off by saying, 'Don't marry this woman!'
So, what kind of woman are we talking about?
“She sees a man of wealth, loses all self-control.”
Oh, come on. The moment they see someone rich and powerful, they forget all about the dignity of their profession as a teacher.
and just rush to suck up to them.
Their minds are no longer focused on how to impart knowledge, teach their craft, and resolve doubts.
to establish the heart of Heaven and Earth,
to secure a livelihood for the people, to carry on the lost teachings of past sages, and to establish peace for all generations to come.
All they can think about is how to maximize their own gains.
This kid doesn't want to learn. He's just not cut out for it.
And you're just teaching for the sake of money and power. Remember, 'A sheer cliff stands a thousand ren high; without desire, one is invincible.'
You're scared of your own shadow, constantly calculating risks and rewards.
Then you can't even talk about educating the child with that firm, yet balanced, virtue anymore.
Even when it's obvious the kid is going down the wrong path,
you wouldn't dare to correct them.
Oh, right.
Oh, right, this is the boss's son.
Or, what if the kid doesn't like me? I could lose my job over it.
blah blah blah...
This kid just has no respect for real knowledge.
and just keep making the same mistakes over and over again.
Over time, this will inevitably lead to a habit of being careless and not thinking.
But you, the educator, are so preoccupied with your own desires and reservations.
Do you still dare to 'tell the first divination, but not the second or third, for the second and third are profane'?
I bet you wouldn't dare.
Because you're worried the parents will complain, 'Why aren't you more patient?'
The commentary in the 'Xiang Zhuan' on this line, 'Do not take the woman, for her conduct is not in accordance,' really hits the nail on the head.
Since ancient times, the divine right of kings has been the rule.
But the way of the teacher can even transcend the way of the ruler.
As the one who imparts the Way, you should not let the masculine principle yield to the feminine.
You shouldn't be like the line 'Seeing a wealthy man, she loses her integrity,' eagerly throwing yourself at him.
You have strayed from the right path!
And this final line, 'nothing is beneficial'...
This means that whether you're the one being this kind of teacher,
or the students who seek guidance from such teachers, it's a lose-lose situation for both sides!
First of all, if you seek knowledge from such a teacher, you will never learn anything of real value.
Because to truly learn something, you need a genuine, heartfelt respect.
Only when you truly take it to heart,
Only then will you truly contemplate the wisdom and mentally digest it.
Only then, in the future, when you apply theory to practice,
Only then will you have that 'aha!' moment, gaining wisdom that will benefit you for a lifetime.
And when your mentor is afraid to be firm and set clear rules for you,
he won't be able to correct your mistakes.
Failing to correct your mistakes is the greatest obstacle and hidden danger to your growth.
If you stray from the right path, the further you go, the bigger the mistake becomes.
the bigger the mistake becomes.
For the mentor who is described by the line 'upon seeing the wealthy man, she loses her integrity'...
Do you really think that just by being a smooth operator and dealing with people superficially,
and get what you want?
For the mentor,
The most crucial metric is whether the student can truly become successful.
Your most enduring legacy is your students.
and will honor you as their mentor for the rest of their lives.
And you think this groveling attitude of yours...
You see mistakes but don't dare to point them out.
acting all timid and cowering in front of your students and employers,
Do you think you can help them succeed?
Will that earn you the respect of your own family?
As an educator, you must first define your own ecological niche.
and have a clear understanding of your own path.
There are many paths and methods to seek progress and prosperity.
Don't take the responsibility of being a role model lightly.
Six in the fourth place: The line statement reads, 'In the困境 of ignorance, there is regret.'
Trapped by ignorance and unable to save oneself.
Seeking enlightenment, but finding no way in.
This is a very regrettable and difficult situation.
Now, as we've mentioned before, the upper trigram represents the learner.
The lower trigram represents the teacher, and this is the fourth six, '困蒙' (Kùn Méng).
A yin line in a yin position symbolizes passivity and refraining from reckless action.
It is in the right position, but not in the center.
It lacks the virtue of centrality and uprightness, and the power to mediate.
It is supported by the Six-Three below and carries the Six-Five above, with both the upper and lower positions being yin.
Both above and below, it's a case of like repelling like.
This leaves it in a state of isolation and helplessness.
This line from the 'Xiang Zhuan' commentary, "The sting of being trapped in ignorance is from being alone and distant from the solid,"
This directly reveals the reason why the fourth six is passively trapped in ignorance.
You have distanced yourself from the 'substantial'.
In other words, it has distanced itself from the two yang lines of this hexagram, the 'Nine in the Second Place' and the 'Nine at the Top'.
This once again emphasizes that the pursuit of knowledge requires a firm foundation of positive, masculine principles.
It requires you, as the yin line, to be proactive. You must seek out the yang lines, to actively search for a worthy teacher.
You're not going to figure it out just by sitting at home!
And this once again echoes the point that the hexagram statement lacks the 'Yuan' or 'Origin' principle.
When it comes to learning, it's not something you can just figure out on your own.
You need a master to show you the way and give you guidance.
It requires an external force.
Even after you've received the true teachings of a theory, you still need to apply it to the real world.
We need to be proactive, to step out and see the world, to engage with all living things.
If we don't seek out mentors, respect them, or ask for their guidance,
just working behind closed doors.
Ultimately, you'll just become more and more closed off, and more and more backward.
and more and more stubborn.
Now, let's look at the fifth six. The line statement says: 'The young and ignorant. Good fortune.'
Now, this 'childlike ignorance' doesn't refer to a kid who's just confused.
It refers to the innocence of a newborn child.
It's a state of being sincere and open to learning, untainted by worldly influences.
Many great sages and powerful individuals still maintain the heart of a child, always eager to learn.
They still maintain this humble and sincere heart.
The 'Xiang Zhuan' commentary explains this as: 'The good fortune of the youthful ignorance is due to its compliance and humility.'
This is precisely referring to the virtue of humility in the 'naive and ignorant'.
The character "Xùn" is often associated with the concept of humility.
This means to yield the imperial throne.
The phrase 'Xùn yǔ zhī yán' in the Analects of Confucius also carries the meaning of being respectful and humble.
In other words, it means to be respectful and humble.
The fifth line, a yin line, is in the ruler's position. Although it is not in its proper place,
Although it is in the ruler's position, it is not in a proper position.
but it is in the central and esteemed position.
Generally speaking,
Those in positions of power often tend to develop flaws like complacency, arrogance, and conceit.
However, the fifth six, despite its position, remains humble, seeking guidance and positioning itself as a student.
positioning itself as an ally.
Avoid the pitfalls of a full moon that begins to wane, or water that overflows when the cup is full.
This is similar to the Ninth Five of the Qian hexagram, 'A flying dragon in the sky. It is beneficial to see the great man.'
This is just like the 'Yellow Skirt, Supreme Good Fortune' in the sixth five line of the Kun hexagram.
It's all about humbling yourself to seek progress.
Whether it's a child or a great figure who has already achieved fame and success,
When this person consistently maintains a humble attitude to seek out their own shortcomings,
seeking out new opportunities for growth and progress.
and to "seek the great man" for the infusion of new blood.
In its noble position as the sixth five, it humbles itself to seek out the ninth two.
To be high in position yet humble.
This is a case of the firm and the yielding corresponding with each other.
This is just as Mencius once said,
A great man is one who has not lost his heart of a newborn child.
And that's why it's destined for good fortune.
The Ninth at the Top.
The line text reads: 'To strike the ignorant is not favorable for being a raider, but favorable for defending against raiders.'
The top ninth line, a yang line in a yin position, is out of place and off-center.
It is in a yin position, which is an improper placement.
This represents the peak of the Gen mountain, and Gen signifies stopping.
This line talks about the bottom line of the Meng Hexagram.
It is the ultimate means of imparting enlightenment and education.
“Ji Meng” means to punish, to strike, to intimidate, and to establish authority.
It's the ultimate method for dealing with unruly kids.
If patient persuasion doesn't work,
or you can just ignore them, as the saying goes, 'if they show contempt, tell them nothing.'
Let him reflect on his own.
But guidance isn't a cure-all.
But if the child doesn't reflect on their actions,
and continues to be mischievous and disruptive,
and shows a blatant disregard for the dignity of the teaching profession,
or even worse, lead other children astray.
Then it's time to discipline them and show them who's in charge.
And it's not just petty people who respect power but not virtue.
Actually, it's the same with kids.
For many problems, it's useless no matter how much you try to reason with them.
A good smack will put them in their place.
It is not advantageous to be the attacker, but advantageous to be the defender.
This tells us the boundary of 'striking the ignorant'.
The boundary of 'attacking' lies in preventing violence and infringement.
If the purpose of 'striking the unenlightened' is to inflict violence or to vent your frustrations,
That is not right.
Our approach to 'striking the ignorant' should be a reactive one.
and to act with a just cause.
The goal is to uphold the fundamental principles of teaching! Punishing ignorance is the last resort and must not be abused.
Only when guidance proves ineffective,
It should only be used when the rules are broken and the right path is defiled.
Punishment is not the goal, nor is it a means of venting.
but rather, to "cultivate correctness through enlightenment."
The goal is to uphold the dignity of our teaching principles, and to be accountable to the masters who came before us.
and below, to be responsible for the children and their families.
If a proper measure of discipline still doesn't work,
we should not escalate the severity or methods of punishment either.
Because why would you waste all that energy getting angry at them?
Why would you even bother hitting him?
This proves that the child is simply not suited for education.
At least for now, it's not a good fit. End the relationship.
It means I'm too old and incompetent. This child should find a better master.
Favorable. I, the teacher, seek the student in their ignorance. The student in their ignorance seeks me.
If the student comes to me, they are ready.
The first divination will give an answer. If you ask again and again, it is an offense, and no answer will be given.
Favorable to be steadfast.
From seeking knowledge to imparting it.
The Meng Hexagram encompasses the full range of responsibilities and obligations for both parties in the educational process.
It also clearly outlines all the stages and conditions.
So, what can we learn from this?
The Xu Hexagram is the fifth of the 64 hexagrams in the I Ching.
Following the creation of Qian, and the bearing of Kun.
The Beginning: Zhun.
Following the Meng Hexagram, which represents the awakening of wisdom,
Now, it's time to explore the matters of our needs and desires.
This is precisely the line from the 'Sequence of Hexagrams': 'Meng, that which is unenlightened, is the infancy of all things.'
Things in their infancy cannot be left ungrown; therefore, the hexagram of Xu follows.
The character 'Xu' signifies the way of sustenance.
The Great Image commentary also summarizes this, saying: 'Clouds above heaven: the image of Waiting. The superior person nourishes himself with food and drink and awaits the time of action.'
The focus here is on "food and drink" and "feasting and entertainment."
These matters of sustaining life and distributing benefits
Now, the 'feasting and music' here doesn't mean just getting wasted and partying, you know.
It serves as a vehicle for uniting the team and distributing benefits.
We'll dive deeper into this when we get to the Ninth Five.
The Xū Hexagram is composed of Kan (Water) above and Qián (Heaven) below, which is why it is also known as 'Water over Heaven.'
That's why it's also called 'Water over Heaven,' with the lower trigram being Heaven.
This means that just as Heaven's course is ever vigorous, a gentleman should constantly strive for self-improvement.
Everything you need must be earned through your own hard work.
The upper trigram is Water.
This means your path ahead is once again fraught with danger.
Actually, have you guys ever noticed something?
The Kan trigram really shows up a lot, doesn't it?!
Starting with the Tun Hexagram,
In fact, the Kan trigram appears in every single hexagram of this initial stage of all things.
After the 'parent' hexagrams of Qian and Kun,
The hexagrams of Zhun, Meng, Xu, Song, Shi, and Bi all contain the Kan trigram within them.
So, what can we take away from all this?
The beginning of all things is fraught with peril.
Especially for this hexagram, the Tuan Zhuan, or the Commentary on the Decision, even directly explains it.
Xu means to wait. It signifies that danger lies ahead. However, if one is firm and strong, one will not be trapped. This is the principle of how one avoids being cornered.
The original meaning of the character "xū" is beard.
In the pre-Qin classics, it was also often used interchangeably with this character, '頫'.
This means 'to wait'.
For instance, in the 'Classic of Poetry,' there's a line that says, 'Others cross the river, but I will not. I will wait for my friend.'
pronounced as "áng"
Heaven will grant five years of grace to their descendants.
In the Zuo Zhuan, it says, "The day is waning, and our lord is waiting."
In all these instances, the character 'xū' carries the meaning of 'to wait'.
What the Commentary on the Tuan says is this:
All your needs require you to wait.
And this requires patience.
You need to think it through and carefully discern whether it's something you truly need.
Because right behind desire lies danger!
Of course, this isn't to say we should just lie flat and give up, you know.
It's not about actively suppressing our desires,
You see, our Chinese ancestors never taught us to be passive.
Even when facing the counsel to 'lie low like a hidden dragon,' or the warning that 'one step on frost means solid ice is near,'
or even 'treading on frost, the solid ice will come'
all of these are reminders for us to act with a low profile and in a proactive way.
This waiting is a proactive process of reflection and introspection, a necessary step to understand your true needs.
and to grasp the fundamental principles that govern how things develop.
If you want the fruits of autumn, you must sow in the spring and toil through the summer!
A noble person loves wealth, but acquires it through righteous means.
Reasonable desires are in accordance with the principles of nature and human nature.
So, the lower trigram is Qian.
This serves as a reminder that we must always strive.
But what is all this striving for?
Is it about the goals and meaning of life,
Or is it just to fall into a never-ending trap of desire?
And so, "The character for 'Need' (需) also signifies 'waiting' (須), as danger lies ahead."
Our ancestors remind us to be mindful of our own needs and desires.
We need to engage in prudent thinking.
We must endure the test of time and the trial of waiting.
It's true that we strive our entire lives,
But we must always be clear about what we're striving for.
This way, as you move forward, you won't be dragged into danger by the great net of desire.
This means 'to be firm and strong, yet not陷 in its righteousness, so it will not be困穷.'
Let's look at the Hexagram Statement: 'Faithfulness brings success, and it is beneficial to be steadfast and upright.'
With sincerity, it will be smooth and successful. Perseverance brings good fortune.
It is beneficial to cross the great river.
First of all, there's another point to note.
Here, we have 'Xiang,' 'Zhen,' and 'Li,' but 'Yuan' is missing.
But what does it mean that there's no 'Yuan'?
Your desires and needs are not something the universe is obligated to fulfill.
Whether it's a human or a beast, a plant or a fish,
be it plants and trees, or fish and insects.
How many young lives perish just moments after they are born?
The universe does, in fact, grant you a chance to begin.
But it's very likely just that: a beginning.
Heaven does indeed have a virtue of cherishing life.
But Heaven also never intervenes. The universe is not benevolent; it treats all things as straw dogs.
Therefore, we should cherish every single meal, remembering how hard it was to come by.
And every single thread reminds us of the toil and hardship involved.
We must cherish our blessings and our resources.
When we are grateful and cherish what we have,
And when we hold this sense of reverence, we are in the right state of being.
Only with a mind as open as a valley can one embrace all rivers.
With sincerity, there is great success, even the crossing of a great river.
The original meaning of this character, 'fú,' is 'to hatch an egg,' and from there, it was extended to mean 'to be trustworthy and faithful.'
Later, its meaning was extended to signify trustworthiness and faithfulness.
As the saying goes, 'Fu' means to hatch an egg, and by extension, to be trustworthy.
Just as a bird hatches its eggs precisely on schedule, it never fails to keep its promise.
Having good fortune.
To be "sincere and trustworthy" means to have a steady and faithful heart, free from frivolity and impetuousness.
It means being able to fulfill your duties diligently and persistently.
This is the prerequisite for waiting, as taught in the Xū hexagram.
When we hold fast to our beliefs, strive to stay on the right path, and patiently await the opportune moment,
our energy will continue to build and grow stronger.
our true needs will become clear in our hearts.
And the path to achieve it will also become clearer through this process of waiting and working hard.
Let's look back at the Monkey King's journey to seek immortality.
He starts off just messing around, acting like a king and a tyrant for three to five hundred years.
He watched wave after wave of monkeys die without feeling a thing.
Until one day, it suddenly hit him, and he was terrified.
Just then, a nearby NPC, the Long-armed Ape, reminds you that you should seek the secret of immortality.
Then, he voyaged far across two vast oceans.
After wandering the mortal world for eight or nine years, I've seen it all and found it wasn't worth it.
I've seen through all the ways of the mortal world.
When will the endless race for fame and fortune ever cease?
Waking early and sleeping late, with no freedom in sight!
Riding a donkey, one longs for a steed; a prime minister, for a king's crown.
Worried only about food and clothes, toiling away, why fear the Grim Reaper's call?
Striving for wealth and honor for their children and grandchildren, not a single one is willing to turn back!
After gaining ample experience and reflecting deeply,
The Monkey King had fortified his conviction.
I don't care what anyone says! I want to live forever!
Once your conviction is firm, it leads to the 'brilliant success' that comes from patient, steady effort.
This "sincerity" is the direction and the foundation.
Through hard work, you will reach a state of clarity and success, where everything flows smoothly and your efforts bear fruit.
This phrase, 'Guang Heng,' also serves as a reminder for us.
A true need is one that aligns with the core principles of light and progress.
Of course, just wanting 'Brightness and Success' and 'Having Faith' is not enough.
But if you're dead set on, say, murder and arson, that's a whole different story!
just 'smooth progress'
You also need the protection of core values.
This is what's meant by the 'steadfastness brings good fortune' that follows.
This is the red line for our needs and our waiting.
Only a wait and a pursuit that adhere to the right path will bring good fortune!
Those actions born of extravagance, reckless impulses, forcing growth, or a shortsighted pursuit of quick success...
will ultimately fall into the pit of danger.
The commentary in the Tuan Zhuan explains it as follows:
“With sincerity, it brings great success and is favorable. It is in the position of Heaven, to be correct and central.”
This means upholding the correct middle way, even when you've reached the highest position.
one must still follow the path of righteousness and not act recklessly.
So, once we have achieved 'sincerity, brightness, smoothness, correctness, and good fortune',
then you will be able to 'ford great rivers.' The phrase 'to ford great rivers' means to cross over perilous waters.
This is a common term in the I Ching.
It means to overcome great dangers and difficulties.
to accomplish great missions and achieve magnificent feats.
Desire itself is not a sin; what matters is whether it aligns with the right path.
But waiting is not an end in itself.
but a strategic response that respects the natural order of things.
The ultimate potential of the Xu Hexagram can be incredibly high.
It's about crossing great rivers to achieve great things!
It's that line from the Commentary on the Tuan, "Beneficial to cross great rivers, for there is merit in going forward!" If becoming a high official is purely for the sake of power and pleasure,
If it's purely for the sake of personal gain and pleasure,
Then that's not the right path. And notice, I said 'solely'.
Ah...
What is considered improper is to prioritize wielding power and enjoying its privileges above all else.
First of all, you should absolutely take advantage of the legitimate benefits and entitlements granted to you as a leader by the state.
If the desire and ambition to hold a high office are driven by the pursuit of one's political ideals,
and to do more tangible things for the country and the people.
That is a great and solemn vow.
Then it is time to cross the great river!
Then, we should dedicate our abilities to the great rejuvenation of the Chinese nation!
The first nine, the line statement reads: 'Waiting in the suburbs. Perseverance brings advantage. No blame.'
As the 'Tuan Zhuan' mentioned earlier, the character 'Xu' (需) means 'to wait'.
The so-called 'suburbs' refer to the area within the city walls, which is the state.
The area 100 li from the capital is the suburbs.
and fifty kilometers beyond the suburbs lies the wilderness.
Another interpretation is: 'Within the royal domain, a hundred li make up the suburbs, two hundred li make up a district, and three hundred li make up the wilderness.'
Two hundred li make a 'zhou'.
Waiting in the Suburbs.
Literally, it means to wait in the suburbs, far from the capital.
The deeper meaning is to wait in a place far from the lure of profit and desire.
The Commentary on the Images adds, "Waiting in the outskirts means not venturing into danger."
This is telling us that at this moment,
One should proactively seek safety in the buffer zone of the郊外,远离 danger.
and not to rashly advance into dangerous territory.
And notice, it's about actively avoiding risk.
This means not rashly heading towards the center of profit while taking on unnecessary risks.
The first nine is a yang line in a yang position. Although it is in the correct position, it is not centered.
Right from the start, you must always play it safe and let the dust settle.
Even the first nine at the bottom of the Qian hexagram is a 'hidden dragon, do not act'.
And it's also a yang line at the very bottom.
This line is also the one that is furthest from the danger of the upper trigram, Kan.
This is the safest stage of the entire hexagram.
So, why is it safe?
Because we're far from the center of the action.
We haven't gotten caught up in the fray.
And this so-called 'waiting in the suburbs' isn't just about physical space, either.
Instead, it means we can step outside the great web of desire.
and look at it from a sufficiently objective
and look at our needs objectively from a detached perspective.
Is it a genuine necessity?
Even if it's a genuine, essential need,
we also need to carefully consider our own vulnerability at this stage.
Is it really necessary to sign up for the rat race?
It's like, we all know that having a place to call our own is a basic necessity.
This is a basic need.
But when we've just entered the workforce, just started our first job,
But is this a need that has to be met right away?
Is it really worth taking on a loan for this 'essential need', and from then on, not daring to take any risks in life?
Once you've bought this house, you won't dare to switch jobs easily.
What if your company doesn't grow?
What if there aren't any good jobs near your little place?
You're completely tied down.
So, wouldn't renting a place be a better idea for now?
So, let's delay satisfying this essential need.
Once we've turned that first pot of gold into something that generates a continuous stream of income for us,
Wouldn't it be better to satisfy this essential need after we've acquired the productive assets that generate a steady income?
we should examine this matter with the attitude of 'needing at the outskirts'.
Then we can make a clear judgment.
If we start thinking about the rise and fall of housing prices, about investing and speculating,
Once you start mixing in things like wedding dowries and all that,
Then it's no longer a matter of 'needing in the suburbs.' We'll just get overwhelmed and confused.
Like we said, we have the power to act.
This is like the First Nine of the Qian hexagram, which represents 'Heaven's ceaseless motion.' Proactively avoiding risks is also a powerful form of action.
Because to克制欲望 and 克制焦虑 means we've conquered ourselves.
This means we've conquered ourselves.
To conquer an enemy is hard, but to conquer yourself is even harder.
Throughout history, there have been very few undefeated generals.
Because the reason they always win is that they 'first make themselves invincible, and then wait for the enemy to be vulnerable.'
We need to hardwire this attitude into our operating system.
This is also what the following line means: 'Perseverance brings no blame.'
When we hold fast to our righteous path with perseverance,
we can avoid disaster.
Notice, it's 'no blame,' 'no disaster,' not 'great fortune.'
What does that mean?
Desires and needs, no matter how essential they may seem,
When it comes down to it, it's all about vanity and self-interest.
It's what everyone is fighting over.
While they are the very source of life, they are also the root of all calamity.
We must guard our hearts at all times.
The second nine: In the sand, there is some talk, but in the end, it is auspicious.
The ultimate sand.
The character 'sha' (沙) refers to a shallow shoal or bank by the water.
The ground here is loose and prone to sinking.
But you won't sink in too deep.
But it's a fleeting danger.
This means we're getting closer to the peril of the Kan trigram than the '郊' (suburbs) of the initial nine.
But you're not in danger yet.
At most, it's like the saying, 'If you play with fire, you're bound to get burned.'
When we no longer want to just watch from a distance,
Or, to put it another way, they've already found their direction.
and their strength is also greater than that of the initial Nine.
So, we start to approach our goal, testing the waters.
But at this point, they are still clear-headed and self-aware.
It's not yet time to dive headfirst into the deep end.
Instead, you should test the waters at the edge of the danger zone.
This is about crossing the river by feeling the stones step-by-step. The following line, 'minor criticism, but ultimate good fortune,' means...
Because when you get close to the gains, you also get close to the danger.
This will inevitably draw criticism, gossip, blame, and condemnation.
But you don't need to worry too much about it.
In the end, we will achieve a favorable outcome.
Now, you might be wondering why that is.
The Commentary on the Images provides further explanation.
Waiting on the sandy ford means being in the middle.
Although there may be some initial criticism, it will ultimately lead to good fortune.
The character '衍' (yǎn) is composed of '行' (xíng), meaning 'to walk' or 'to go,' on the outside, and '水' (shuǐ), meaning 'water,' on the inside.
This signifies that the river channel is unobstructed, allowing the water to flow freely.
The Shuowen Jiezi states, "To 'Yan' is for all waters to converge upon the sea."
This idea of all rivers flowing into the sea was then extended to mean 'to extend, to spread, and to be abundant'.
This 'centrality' means that the second line, a yang line, is in a yin position.
Although it is not in its proper position, it is centered.
But the second line, it's in the central position.
Generally speaking, for any line, whether Yin or Yang, being in the central position means things won't turn out too badly.
The commentary in the Xiang Zhuan describes this state as being like waiting on a shallow sandbank, right on the edge of danger.
This means there's plenty of room and a wide margin for error.
so it won't lead to any major dangers.
If you take a small step forward and feel like something's not right, you can immediately pull back.
and pull back right away.
Since we've started moving towards the center of the action,
Then you're doomed to step into a battlefield of slander and a sea of conflict.
This 'minor criticism' is simply unavoidable.
And don't think it gets any easier. The further you go, the more it's going to hurt.
He who is praised by all is also slandered by all.
Being the subject of some gossip is an inevitable price for anyone who gains an advantage.
This assurance of 'ultimate good fortune' must be because...
Given your position and mindset at this moment, you're truly in a safe spot.
Because you are 'advancing from a central position'.
You have a buffer, both in terms of physical space and your state of mind.
The sand, the shallows by the water, act as a buffer zone.
So even if a huge wave suddenly crashes in, it won't be strong enough to sweep you away.
It's not like the next line, "Waiting in the mud."
But once you're stuck in the mud, it's not so easy to pull yourself out.
The point is, you can always pull back without fear.
This safety buffer also helps us maintain a balanced and centered mindset, free from extremism.
Not be provoked by petty remarks, nor argue with rumors.
Resolve conflicts with a tolerant and open mind.
Petty gossip is never a real obstacle.
As long as you don't let it mess with your head,
as long as you stick to your own pace and feel your way forward cautiously.
petty talk will never escalate into a major disaster.
Just take it as a bit of fun.
Of course, having come this far, we still need to be mentally prepared.
From now on, there will always be people talking.
It's a relentless assault, one wave crashing in before you can even catch your breath from the last.
Just don't let it get to you.
If you get too hung up on what other people say,
You'd better just turn around and head back to the 'suburbs'.
You're still not quite ready yet.
You need to go back and temper your mind a bit more.
The line text for the third nine says, "Waiting in the mud brings robbers near." This phrase, "waiting in the mud"...
Now, you've reached the muddy banks by the water.
One more step and you're in the river.
At this point, any big wave could come and sweep you right into the river.
Or even, you could just slip and fall right into the river.
So, you might wonder, why is the trigram 'Kan', which is associated with the water element in the Five Elements, defined as 'danger'?
Now, when you guys go to the river to hang out today,
Even if you're standing really close to the river,
we usually don't think much of it.
That's because the rivers we see in parks or around us today have usually been renovated.
They've usually been renovated.
The embankments slope gently into the river, providing a gradual transition.
But in ancient times,
Many rivers hide traps that can suddenly cause you to fall.
Perhaps you're just a single step away from the shore,
But if you take that one step forward, you'll find out.
The riverbed suddenly drops off vertically, as if it's been sliced by a knife.
In an instant, the water goes from knee-deep to two, three, or even more than ten meters deep!
From the initial Nine to the third Nine, we see a gradual progression from the 'suburbs,' a distant risk, to the 'sand,' a closer one, and finally to the 'mud,' where the danger is imminent.
“Waiting in the mud” means we have now reached a point of considerable danger.
This is a critical point of safety and danger, where your footing is unstable and you can easily fall into a predicament with no easy escape.
But despite the danger,
that doesn't mean we shouldn't move forward.
The lower trigram of the Xū Hexagram is the Qian Hexagram, symbolizing the vigorous movement of Heaven.
It's about being proactive while you wait.
Remember what the Tuan Zhuan says?
The character 'xū' in 'xū guà' means 'to need' or 'to require', and it signifies that danger lies ahead.
If one is firm and strong, yet does not fall into the pit, then one's path will not be one of hardship and poverty.
It's not telling us to just wait endlessly.
Once we've carefully discerned the situation,
Once you've identified the right opportunity and direction,
We have to keep moving forward. We can't let the fear of choking stop us from eating.
You can't let the fear of a cricket's chirp stop you from planting your crops.
But any action you take will inevitably involve some risk.
But as long as we have the right methods and resources to handle them, we'll be fine.
We'll head for the section of the river that's the least risky.
If we want to cross the Yellow River, we can just take the Pujin Ferry. That's a perfectly good option.
We don't have to insist on crossing at Longmen Ferry, the one from the legend of the carp leaping over the dragon gate.
and try to brute-force our way through the thundering, massive Yellow River.
Our ultimate goal is to ford the great river, to achieve something significant.
It's about taking calculated risks to achieve your goal.
All we need to do is get to the Guanzhong region.
Ultimately, we're here to do something big!
Crossing the river is the goal, but our real purpose is to be the first to enter the Guanzhong region and claim the throne.
Just getting across the river is all that matters.
Don't you dare go running off to Longmen Ferry to risk your neck for a chance at life!
When we are just one step away from the gate of profit,
This means that all sorts of misfortunes, like robbers, legal troubles, and natural disasters, are about to befall us.
In other words, 'bringing the robbers to your door.'
So, when all sorts of external calamities come knocking,
And once they arrive,
So, what should we do?
This is what the 'Xiang Zhuan' says:
To be stuck in the mud means disaster is coming from the outside. If you bring trouble upon yourself, you must be cautious and respectful to avoid defeat.
This 'reverence' means to be in awe. It's about having a deep reverence for the laws of nature, for boundaries, and for the risks of disaster.
Do not act recklessly just because you are powerful.
Don't leave things to chance.
And 'Shen' means being cautious.
It means making steady, solid progress without rushing forward, taking every step with caution.
Cultivate reverence to govern your mind, and practice prudence to govern your actions.
By upholding this attitude,
This is how you can remain invincible amidst all kinds of dangers.
After Liu Bang fought his way into the Guanzhong region, he got a big head and lost his cool.
He really started thinking he was the king of Guanzhong.
Then he blocked the Hangu Pass, nearly getting himself killed in the process.
His state at that moment was exactly 'Waiting in the Mud'.
He's already in too deep.
What was truly remarkable was his ability to slam on the brakes and retreat to Bashang.
He retreated to Bashang with a posture of reverence and caution.
He pulled off a series of incredibly difficult maneuvers.
Xiang Bo and Xiang Yu's two rounds of crisis management
Before we can charge towards our ultimate goal, we all go through a phase of being 'bogged down in the mud'.
There's always a phase of trudging through the mud.
During this stage, we need to keep a low profile.
and keep a low profile.
Create the impression that you've just happened upon the riverbank by chance.
This way, you can avoid being overwhelmed by blows from all sides before you're ready.
Getting taken out before you even step into the ring.
As for the officials and bandits lying in wait, looking for trouble,
Respond with a respectful and cautious attitude, neither humble nor arrogant.
After all, there's no real proof that we've actually entered the fray.
As long as there's no hard evidence, you can always talk your way out of it.
I, Liu Bang, might have courted death for a moment there.
But I pulled back.
I'm just here, exercising caution and self-control, waiting for my dear Secretary Xiang.
So you can't make a move on me.
Whether you're strategizing against enemies on the battlefield or scheming for a position in the political arena,
or in the preparatory phase of charging ahead to make a profit in the business world.
The principle is the same across the board.
Six in the Fourth Place.
The line statement says: 'Waiting in the blood, one emerges from the pit.'
In the last line, it was before we had even stepped into the deep waters of the river of profit.
This is before we've even stepped into the deep waters of the great river of profit.
And just as they got their feet wet, they had already 'attracted the bandits'.
and you've already invited the bandits to come and get you.
Xiang Yu had already mocked him, saying, "Oh, so the King of Guanzhong has arrived."
Hey.
Now, we have officially entered the core peril of the upper trigram, Kan, which represents danger.
So, it's time to get out the knives.
This line, 'needing to emerge from a pit of blood,'
This describes the intensifying conflicts of interest and escalating contradictions at this stage.
The situation has escalated to a perilous point, one where blood will be shed.
Unlike the first three lines where the danger was external,
Instead, the danger is now upon us.
At this point, no one can save us. We need to 'emerge from the pit'.
We have to find our own way out of the danger.
So, how do we get out?
This is how the Commentary on the Images explains it.
One must wait amidst the blood, and listen by following the current.
Here, "顺应" (shùn yìng) means to go with the flow, rather than going against the current or being rigid.
This line, the fourth six, is a yin line in a yin position, which emphasizes the importance of going with the flow.
At this point, we've entered the deep end.
If we charge head-on against the perilous current
Either we'll quickly exhaust all our strength,
or, without even touching them, our boat capsizes and we're done for.
Any attempt to be reckless or confrontational will only cause us to lose our strength even faster.
and sink us deeper and deeper.
We need to conserve our energy.
Only by moving with the current can you avoid being swallowed by the treacherous waves.
We need to be clear about the advantage we're trying to gain.
If you want to cross this river, you'll find yourself surrounded by a massive crowd of competitors.
Countless heroes and outstanding figures have plunged into these perilous waters to do battle.
At this very moment, no matter how powerful we as individuals might be,
is never enough against the tide of history.
I mean, Xiang Yu was an absolute beast in a fight.
He was the one who, by his own strength, changed the course of the late Qin dynasty.
But in the end, he was defeated by Liu Bang, Han Xin, Ying Bu, and Chen Ping.
And this gang of former underlings? They were all drowned out in the great river of the late Qin dynasty.
Even though he was victorious in every battle, he was ultimately defeated by his own string of successes.
The use of the character 'tīng' (听) in the phrase 'shùn yǐ tīng' (顺以听) is particularly brilliant.
First, let's look at the hexagram's imagery.
According to the 'Shuogua Zhuan' or 'Discussion of the Trigrams' from the 'I Ching',
Qian represents the head, Kun the abdomen, Zhen the foot, and Xun the thigh.
Kan corresponds to the ear, Li to the eye, Gen to the hand, and Dui to the mouth.
So, it says here that the Kan trigram represents the ear.
So, the character for 'listening' is a perfect match for the trigram's symbolism from the very beginning.
Being in the peril of Kan is like being plunged into a land of darkness.
Your eyes can't see the whole picture,
and can't tell which way to go.
That's why it's crucial to calm down and listen carefully.
The essence of "listening" is that the more dangerous the environment, the more you need to remain calm.
Secondly, "listening" isn't about passive conformity or just going with the flow.
but rather, it's about discerning right from wrong.
It means to perceive the subtle and profound.
The first is appearance, the second is speech, the third is observation, the fourth is listening, and the fifth is thought.
Demeanor should be reverent, speech should be compliant, and vision should be clear.
Speech should be compliant, and vision should be clear.
Listening leads to discernment, and thinking leads to wisdom.
Respectfulness leads to solemnity, compliance leads to order, and clarity leads to wisdom.
Cleverness leads to strategy, and wisdom leads to sagehood.
The character '听' (tīng), which means 'to listen' or 'to hear', implies being intelligent, discerning, and perceptive to the finest detail.
For instance, the term 'judging a case'.
This is the principle of 'adjudicating the lawsuits of the people with the Five Punishments, and supplementing the punishments with intelligence and reports.'
For instance, "attending to governance."
This means that when the king holds court to govern, the ministers are to support and listen to his judgments. The same principle applies when the king receives reports from the four directions.
What's emphasized is a state of complete clarity.
Take, for example, that famous saying from Confucius.
At fifteen, I set my heart on learning.
At thirty, I stood firm. At forty, I had no more doubts.
At forty, I had no more doubts.
At fifty, I knew the mandate of Heaven.
At sixty, my ears were attuned. At seventy, I could follow my heart's desire without transgressing the boundaries.
Now, this 'being receptive to all sounds' isn't just about getting old.
and become a cheerful old man who can take anything in stride.
So, the old man is just having a good time, huh?
Instead, it builds upon the idea of "knowing the will of Heaven at fifty."
and serves as the key to understanding "At seventy, I can follow my heart's desire without transgressing the boundaries."
It means, 'When your ears are attuned, you hear words and understand their subtle meaning.'
It's that after hearing just one sentence from someone,
You get what they really mean without even having to think twice.
I get what he's trying to say.
The other person might not even realize they've already shown their hand.
And the 60-year-old master has already seen through it all.
This state of 'ear-obedience' is precisely what is meant here by 'obeying to listen'.
So, the use of the word 'listen' here is just brilliant.
For instance, 'to follow with compliance,' 'to avoid with compliance,' 'to receive with compliance.'
or "Shun to achieve"
it just doesn't have that flavor of wisdom.
To be 'needing in blood' is to listen with compliance.
Whether it's 'yielding' or 'listening'
Both of these, in fact, emphasize the idea of waiting, which is the essence of 'Xu'.
In the torrent of danger, your first priority is to preserve your own strength.
The first priority is to preserve your own strength.
Follow the prevailing trend with a calm mind.
and use a sharp mind to analyze the situation and find a way to safety.
After Han Xin argued that this was the only window of opportunity to conquer the empire, and that if they faltered now, they would lose their momentum forever,
Liu Bang was able to ignore the advice of Zhang Liang, whose suggestions had always been foolproof, and instead rapidly advanced to pacify the Three Qins.
sword
and swiftly reclaimed the Three Qins.
After the disastrous defeat at Pengcheng, when Zhang Liang revealed who the three heroes for conquering Chu were,
Liu Bang then swiftly redeployed Han Xin to the north to open up a second front.
He went to Huainan to persuade Ying Bu, and to Liang to secure Peng Yue's allegiance.
When Han Xin, after conquering Qi, demanded to be made the acting King of Qi, and Liu Bang was, in theory, powerless to refuse,
He was magnanimous enough to make him a true king.
When he broke the treaty at the Hong Canal and pursued the Western Chu forces,
When faced with the threats of Peng Yue and Han Xin, who were holding out for a price before committing their troops,
He was able to swallow his pride and grant them territories.
When the final defeat of Chu was at hand,
Liu Bang was able to swallow his pride, hand over command, and let the God of War have his ultimate showdown with the Hegemon-King.
The more danger you're in, the more you need to keep a cool head.
Go with the flow and spot the opportunities.
Don't just foolishly and blindly charge ahead!
Instead of just charging in like a fool.
You must constantly break down the components,
and continuously unite the widest range of forces.
and constantly use your superior forces to avoid the strong and attack the weak.
To wait amidst bloodshed means to follow the situation and listen to its dictates.
This is the principle and wisdom that our ancestors have long since summarized for us.
From the hidden perils of a distant swamp, to the treacherous sands in plain sight.
then to the manifest mud,
and finally, to the blood that seeps in.
If you do take the risk and succeed,
It is advantageous to cross the great river.
Alright, next up we have the Ninth Five.
“Waiting upon wine and food, it is favorable to be steadfast and upright.”
First, let's talk about what 'wine and food' actually means here.
This line isn't saying that after you've profited from a risky situation, you can just kick back, relax, and party all the way to the bank.
In ancient societies, "food and wine" were the central elements of sacrificial rites and hospitality.
It's not just about 'Things in their infancy must be nurtured; therefore, it is followed by the Hexagram of Xu.'
nor is it just the way of eating for sustenance and survival, as mentioned in the 'Xu' hexagram.
but also represents the rites of sacrificial and the feasting of sages.
and a governance that benefits all people.
It's not merely a symbol of indulgence.
So, to understand a pre-Qin classic like the I Ching, you have to compare it with other famous works from the same period.
For instance, the "Record of Music" in the Book of Rites states the following.
I'm not going to read this part out loud.
So, let's break down what that means.
The purpose of brewing wine is not to create calamity.
But it's also true that alcohol is something that amplifies the evil in human nature.
That's why the ancient kings established specific rituals for drinking.
Even for the most basic form of this ritual, the 'One-Offering Ceremony',
This means when the host offers a toast to the guest, this single offering is called 'One Offering'.
There were also quite complex rituals to be observed between the host and the guest.
Here, 'a hundred bows' is a figure of speech to describe its complexity.
So you could drink this wine all day and still not get drunk.
All that hustle and bustle? It's all been metabolized and pissed away.
It's all just metabolized and gone.
All of this is to prevent the disasters that can come from drinking.
So, the purpose of food and wine is to bring people together.
a legitimate means to bond and share joy.
The 'Rites of Zhou, Chapter of the Grand Minister of Sacrifices' records: 'Use the rites of food and drink to draw near to the kinsmen and brothers.'
and to use the rites of feasting to welcome guests from all corners of the world.
explicitly designated feasting and drinking as a means to unite the clan,
and the key ritual for winning over guests.
This means that wine was only to be used for sacrificial rituals! Heaven, in its divine will, created wine for the people,
Its purpose was for everyone to use during grand sacrificial ceremonies!
Heaven sent down its punishment, the people fell into chaos, and morality was lost.
And it was all because of the reckless behavior caused by excessive drinking.
King Wen warned his descendants not to drink without reason, and especially not to overindulge in alcohol.
He even established a rule for the vassal states: they were only permitted to drink during sacrificial ceremonies.
Even during sacrifices, one must not be greedy with the cup and get drunk.
Such behavior is a breach of decorum and a failing of virtue.
So, what profound meaning do "wine and food" represent, after all?
First, it represents gratitude to Heaven.
After successfully crossing the great river and profiting from the shore, one must maintain a sense of reverence and be grateful for the blessings received.
Secondly, it represents the maintenance of order.
It's the core method for uniting forces.
At the same time, it also means that you must share the benefits with your own team.
This is the oath Liu Bang made when he was about to confer titles and ranks.
This is the oath Liu Bang made when he was about to grant titles and fiefdoms.
This would make the Yellow River as narrow as a belt and Mount Tai as smooth as a whetstone, so that the state may be preserved forever, and this love may extend to the descendants.
Secondly, it represents the caution of not indulging in desires and always being as prudent as walking on thin ice.
This is the same "zhēn" from the line statement, "Waiting on wine and food, it is auspicious to be steadfast."
as well as the "uprightness" in the Xiang Zhuan, which says, "Good fortune in feasting and drinking comes from uprightness."
All of this is telling us...
This is from the line: 'Clouds rise to the heavens. This is the image of Waiting. In accordance with this, the superior man eats and drinks, and is of good cheer.'
This is a balance you must always get right!
So, what does this mean for us?
Generally speaking,
After surviving the storm, fighting tooth and nail, and finally making it big,
There are three major pitfalls that await.
First, they get a big head and forget who they are.
They feel their abilities are so immense they're practically bursting at the seams.
You start to lose your sense of reverence.
They start thinking they can do anything.
And what follows this arrogance is a great disaster.
Second, greedily monopolizing all the credit.
They cling tightly to their profits, refusing to share with the brothers who have weathered the storm with them.
unwilling to share with those who
the brothers who've been through thick and thin with you
And what follows is being deserted by everyone.
So, how exactly did Xiang Yu meet his end?
So why did guys like Han Xin and Chen Ping all jump ship?
So why, despite being such a great warrior, did he end up with fewer and fewer people on his side?
So, what was the reason?
Because he doesn't share the rewards!
He'd rather wear the corners off his official seal than give out a single reward!
Everything you wouldn't reward, Old Liu went and rewarded for you.
He let Old Liu take care of all the rewards.
Third, indulging in pleasure without restraint.
This attracts a crowd of disreputable friends, as well as wolves and tigers.
squandering both their health and their wealth.
Our ancestors summed this up in just six words: 'Waiting over wine and food, perseverance brings good fortune.'
This clearly tells us the right mindset to have once we've made it to shore.
First, by offering sacrifices to Heaven, Earth, and our ancestors, we can quiet our minds.
Paying respects to our ancestors helps us quiet our minds.
and return to a state of calm.
Second, use sacrificial rites and feasts to unite the team and strengthen cohesion.
This makes your team feel that following you is a path to a better future, where everyone gets their share of the rewards.
And together, you will march from one victory to the next!
Third, by observing the absolute restrictions and warnings regarding alcohol set by the ancient sages and worthies.
and remind yourself not to get lost in the pursuit of pleasure.
Although the ninth five line is in the correct position and central, which is a great auspiciousness for the ruler's hexagram,
and is considered a great and auspicious hexagram.
But at the end of the day, this is still the middle line of the upper trigram, Kan, which represents danger.
After all, you're in a dangerous situation, so you must be vigilant at all times!
My friends, after we've weathered the storm and made it to shore, having left countless others behind,
and look back on the mountains of corpses and seas of blood left in the wake of that peril.
We must remember the playbook our ancestors gave us for navigating this stage.
So, what are the key strategies for this phase?
So whatever you do, don't get cocky, don't get reckless, don't be stingy, and don't give in to your every whim.
First off, I've just got to give a huge shout-out to our brilliant ancestors.
Such profound wisdom.
For those of you who've been through the wringer, you know exactly how much weight that last part really carries!
The Sixth, at the Top
The line text reads: 'Entering the cave, three uninvited guests arrive. If you treat them with respect, it will be auspicious in the end.'
If, after successfully crossing the great river, you fail to follow the path of centrality and correctness of the Ninth Five,
You get carried away, go wild, become stingy, and court disaster.
Well, that's a shame.
And with that, you arrive at the top sixth line of the Xu hexagram.
This is the ultimate position of peril, the very peak of the dangerous upper trigram, Kan.
Kan represents a pit, a cave, and perilous difficulties.
Entering the pit of hardship.
“Entering the pit” means you have fallen into a perilous and desperate situation.
At this point, you're at a dead end, trapped and with no one to help.
And don't ask why. You've got no one to blame but yourself.
Your arrogance and extravagance will make everyone jealous and resent you.
and now everyone resents you for it.
You don't share the profits, so your key people leave you.
Everyone is just waiting for you to fail, watching you as a joke!
Everyone's just waiting for you to fail, watching you like it's a joke.
Not only will no one come to help you anymore,
And at this point, 'three uninvited guests arrive.'
Here, the character 'su' (速) means to invite or to summon.
On the surface, an 'uninvited guest' is simply a visitor who shows up without being asked.
But in reality, it carries a more negative connotation, referring to unwelcome intruders with ill intentions.
The term 'three people' here doesn't literally mean three individuals.
Here, the number 'three' represents a multitude.
In other words,
When you reach the top sixth line of the Xu hexagram, you have entered the very heart of the Kan, the abyss of danger.
a whole host of uninvited guests will come crashing into your life.
To put it in Buddhist terms,
This means wealth is jointly owned by five types of entities, as stated in the Mahāprajñāpāramitā Śāstra.
We toil for wealth, yet it is shared by five others.
shared by our own family.
be it by the king, by thieves, by fire, by flood, or by your own unvirtuous children.
Even what you bury will be lost.
In other words, legal disasters, theft, floods, fires, and prodigal children.
If you disrespect the heavens, disasters of water and fire will befall you.
If you live extravagantly or are miserly, calamities from officials and thieves will come to take your wealth.
If you don't believe in karma, then you will be ruined by your own unworthy descendants, leading to the bankruptcy of your family.
So, what should you do in this situation?
Our ancestors have already told us.
If you maintain this reverence, you will ultimately find good fortune.
If the arrival of these uninvited guests can serve as a wake-up call for us,
and make us wake up and repent,
and once again adopt an attitude of reverence, respect, and prudence in how we conduct ourselves.
No matter what kind of uninvited guest comes to snatch and plunder,
If we can realize that this disaster is one of our own making,
Then, these uninvited guests are actually the benefactors in our lives.
It's what allows us to break these bad habits.
and make it possible for us to make a comeback in the future.
No matter how severe this uninvited guest might be,
as long as you regain your sense of reverence and caution.
it usually won't be a fatal blow.
Even in the absolute worst-case scenario,
meaning they could strip you of all your resources and status,
But the experiences and the lessons you've gained along the way...
and the invaluable lessons you've learned—no one can ever take those away from you!
and no one can ever take that away from you.
We still have a chance to start over!
But have you guys ever noticed something?
If the Kan trigram appears in the lower trigram,
This means that the first, second, and third lines—Initial Six, Nine Two, and Six Three—are all out of their proper positions.
But if it appears in the upper trigram,
Even if it represents danger,
However, the Six in the Fourth, the Nine in the Fifth, and the Six at the Top are all in their proper positions, and all hold the potential for a turning point.
So, what does that mean?
Now, when it comes to these hardships, encountering them right at the very beginning is extremely perilous!
Every step is a struggle, a life-or-death battle!
Many people run into trouble right when they're just starting out.
Or you get physically wiped out, and see you in the next life.
Or, they just mentally check out, bow their heads, and resign themselves to a life of fear and mediocrity.
But if you've already got some foundation...
and a certain amount of experience,
and then you encounter them after you've built up enough of a foundation,
It's an unavoidable part of starting any venture.
Every trial that doesn't kill me only makes me stronger!
Even if you're knocked back to square one, even if you've lost everything you had,
But you can still start all over again!
The Hexagram of Xu is about the acquisition and distribution of resources.
So, after explaining the first six lines of the hexagram,
So, has this sparked any new thoughts for you all about the process of gaining benefits and the principles of distribution?
The Hexagram of Xu is unique in that it doesn't possess the 'Yuan' quality.
Because resources are always finite.
If you succeed in gaining a profit, it means someone else has failed to get it.
which means someone else has failed to get their share.
And this, in turn, means that conflicts are bound to arise.
and even lead to conflict.
This then leads to resorting to legal means and public authority to resolve the conflict. In other words, as it is said, 'The Way of Nourishment.'
Where there are disputes over food and drink, there will inevitably be litigation. Therefore, the hexagram of 'Dispute' follows.
The hexagram of 'Xu', which deals with the principles of sustenance, has a trigram of Water above and Heaven below.
Except for the Second Yang line, which is out of place, all the other five lines are in their proper positions.
And the only line that's not in its proper place, the Ninth Two, is still central.
This shows that the heavens are extremely supportive of us finding our place, sustaining our lives, and building our legacies.
It is a matter of utmost support.
As long as you remember that the core principle is to wait,
As long as a noble person keeps their talents hidden and acts at the opportune moment,
Acquire and allocate resources in a reasonable manner.
This is the fundamental law of the universe!
But now, the hexagram of litigation is completely the opposite.
Qian above, Kan below.
The first six, the second nine, the third six, the fourth nine, the fifth nine, and the top nine.
Except for the ninth five, all the other lines are out of place!
And right here, we can see why.
This whole idea of litigation is fundamentally inauspicious from the very root.
This is something that every single one of us should do our utmost to avoid.
So, looking at the hexagram of 'Conflict' as a whole,
Nor is it about teaching us how to win a lawsuit.
Instead, it serves as a reminder for us to be cautious about litigation and to stop it whenever possible.
讼, which means to litigate.
Don't resort to litigation unless it's absolutely the last option!
Now, let's look at the Hexagram Statement.
It says, "Sincerity is blocked, be alert." Now, as we mentioned in the commentary on the previous hexagram,
The character '孚' (fú) signifies faithfulness and trustworthiness.
Here, the character 'zhì' (窒) means to be blocked or obstructed.
and "惕" (tì) means to be vigilant and prudent.
So, the phrase 'you fu zhi ti' means...
Even if you are in the right and acting in good faith at this moment,
and you have every right and all the proof to back you up,
Even if your legitimate rights and interests have been violated,
Even if we are completely in the right,
and the person you're up against is a complete bastard who maliciously twists the facts to bully an honest person.
But even then, we must still think twice before taking that final step of going to court.
and whether you can bring your own powerful backers to the table.
Resolve it privately beforehand through communication, negotiation, or even deterrence.
You must always maintain a sense of reverence for the judiciary and public authority.
If you can avoid going to court,
If you can settle things privately, you should always do so beforehand.
And why is that? Because in ancient times, you'd be dealing with a whole pack of corrupt officials who were like wolves and jackals.
There's an old saying: 'An official's ruling has ten possible paths, nine of which are hidden from the public.' What does that mean?
In ancient times, the verdict for the very same lawsuit...
The punishment could be light or severe, the verdict could be a win or a loss.
There were no fixed standards.
The intricacies of these matters were completely unknown to the vast majority of common people.
In a case like this, as long as there's the slightest room for maneuver,
And the presiding officials? Well, the things they can do next are just endless.
Take the 'Studebaker Boy' from the TV series 'Lurk' for example.
So, how did he go about handling those gold bars for the station chief?
That's called showing leniency to a meritorious subject!
You see, this Regiment Commander Xu, he made great contributions during the war of resistance.
He's a war hero, after all. You can't just wipe them all out!
So, how did our dear 'Jade Throne Golden Buddha' get his hands on Liu Yu's most prized treasure?
how did he manage to get Liu Yu's most treasured possession,
And get it into the hands of his wife?
Because Yu Zecheng has leverage over the major corrupt official's sister.
The discretion to determine whether they count as an accomplice.
If Ji Weimin wanted to keep his sister safe,
he would never dare to mention that his loot once included a jade throne and a golden Buddha.
So why did the station chief have the nerve to shamelessly shake down the major traitor, Mu Liancheng?
Because he's the one who holds the power to decide whether this old geezer is a traitor or not.
If I declare you a traitor, all your property will be confiscated.
But if I say you're not...
So, how do you think we should split up your family fortune?
In ancient times,
Once the authorities find any pretext to drag you into it,
They'll skin you alive if they get the chance!
So, how did Song Jiang get so rich?
That's because all his life, he's had a passion for befriending heroes of the martial world.
But if anyone came to seek his help, regardless of their status or background, he would take them in without exception.
He would have them stay at his manor, providing them with food and lodging.
He would spend his days in their company, never tiring of their presence.
And if anyone wanted to leave and start their own journey, he would do everything in his power to fund them.
He was truly a spendthrift, treating gold as if it were dirt.
Because Song Jiang was serving as a clerk in Yuncheng County.
He was a master of both writing and administration, highly skilled in the ways of the bureaucracy.
The phrase 'master of the knife and brush' refers to the ancient practice of carving characters onto bamboo slips to record events.
and used a knife to scrape off any mistakes.
son
Basically, whenever the term 'knife and brush' appears,
Nine times out of ten, it's used with a negative connotation.
In ancient times, these two characters were especially favored in the biographies of cruel officials.
So, why was Song Jiang so obsessed with befriending heroes from the martial world?
Because he needed to use these social outlaws to build a reputation that commanded respect in both the legal and criminal worlds, creating his own kind of 'Studebaker influence'.
and the influence of a Studebaker.
Within the system, he was the Clerk of Yuncheng, a master of officialdom.
Outside the system, he was Song Jiang, the man with connections in the entire underworld of Shandong and Hebei.
This influence, spanning both the legitimate and the underworld, can be summed up in one simple phrase in the market.
The price I, Song Jiang, set is one that's accepted by both the Yuncheng County Court and the heroes of the martial world.
For the cases I handle, just pay up, by the book.
I make my fortune by keeping things peaceful and pleasant.
If you want to save that money, if you want to break the rules...
And Brother Gongming, of course, wouldn't say a word either, just chuckling it off.
He frowns,
Then, the captain of Yuncheng and the heroes of the Jianghu would naturally help that person disappear.
Because you were cutting off Brother Song Jiang's source of income.
You're basically cutting off the bailiffs' bonuses.
You're basically taking away the heroes' insurance.
For example,
So, when a case involving a hero or a wealthy family landed in Song Jiang's hands...
So, what's Clerk Song's move?
He would alter the testimony and falsify the case files.
Change 'murder' to 'manslaughter'...
Change 'robbery' to 'theft' with just a little tweak.
And that completely changes the nature of the crime.
Or even just delete or lose key evidence outright.
Even for those high-profile, seemingly unsolvable cases, he's got his ways.
If there's really no way to tamper with the evidence, I'll just tip them off, right?
So, how did Chao Gai and his crew manage to get away?
With Song Jiang, a serious crime could be reduced to a minor one.
A prime suspect can be downgraded to an accomplice, and a minor offense can be dismissed as no offense at all.
So, that brings us to the question:
So, were all these "heroes of the rivers and lakes" that Song Jiang helped really good people?
In the novel "Water Margin," the term "jianghu" broadly refers to the world outside of the official system.
And that's why the word "heroes" needs to be in quotation marks.
essentially referring to the destabilizing elements in society.
Just how famous was Song Jiang?
that means just as many truly good people were being treated unjustly.
And Song Jiang wasn't some isolated case back in ancient times.
Once a matter escalates to the point of a lawsuit,
In essence, it's just the plaintiff and the defendant constantly funneling money into the government's coffers.
Even if the rich and powerful commit murder and arson with irrefutable proof,
the authorities can still drag things out with all sorts of excuses.
For instance, they might deliberately transfer the case to another yamen.
to increase the litigation costs for the victim.
For instance, they might arrange for court staff to be on a business trip, bringing the case to a standstill.
They drag the victim's family down until they are utterly bankrupt.
forcing you to settle out of court.
They could even fabricate a whole new case.
For instance, they might send a bunch of local thugs to the victim's place to stir up trouble.
and frame the victim for stealing their stuff.
and a whole gang of thugs can all testify. It's the classic Lai Junchen playbook, right?
That's the same old playbook as Lai Junchen.
And then, they'd just lock the victim up.
Then they'd just wait until the victim was tormented to death in prison.
And this became the primary condition for officials in ancient cases who just wanted to get things done quickly.
And with the victim gone...
And then, they'd just pass a sentence, casually.
In ancient times,
If you're quite wealthy, but don't have any backing from the authorities,
Those jackals with powerful backers
They might even fabricate lawsuits against you, just like we mentioned.
They'll drag you into their schemes and bleed you dry.
So, why was it that in ancient times, excelling in studies was the path to becoming a government official?
So, why did having male heirs mean everything in ancient times?
Having more men in the family meant higher productivity.
This means that even before the family falls to its final, fatal line,
And there's always that last desperate path, where you fight to the death and take everyone down with you.
This means that before corrupt officials or bandits decide to wipe you out, they have to weigh the costs.
So, do you see now why it says 'sincerity brings apprehension'?
Let's continue to the next part.
It says, "Moderate success, but an ominous end. It is favorable to meet a great man, but unfavorable to cross the great river."
This sets the core tone for the Lawsuit Hexagram.
It tells us the boundaries between fortune and misfortune when it comes to litigation.
Now, the "middle" in "middle good fortune" doesn't mean that the middle of the dispute is auspicious.
This 'middle' means knowing when to stop,
It means not being extreme or stubborn.
This is exactly what the Commentary on the Tuan explains in the line: 'Favorable in the center, because the firm has arrived at the center.'
The firm comes and attains the center.
This means that litigation should only be a last resort.
or even just a deterrent weapon.
If the other party is willing to back down and start talking properly,
and are willing to talk, even if you still end up losing out a little,
as long as it's not a devastating blow,
as long as they're scared enough afterwards to stop hurting us,
So, it's best to quit while you're ahead.
Never, ever press your advantage relentlessly or be unforgiving when you're in the right!
Back in the day, you had to remember one thing: compared to corrupt officials, common thieves were nothing!
Getting into lawsuits is just asking for trouble, a recipe for disaster.
It's a bottomless pit.
As long as you can cut your losses in time, that's a huge win!
That would be the best possible outcome.
If this whole thing drags on endlessly,
Even if you have every right on your side, fighting to the bitter end will inevitably lead to disaster.
the outcome will inevitably be disastrous.
First of all, the authorities will do everything in their power to squeeze every last drop of property from both the plaintiff and the defendant.
Even if you ultimately win the lawsuit,
But you will have already lost the very foundation to make a comeback.
But what's even more critical is this:
After a life-or-death struggle,
So, what do you do when your opponent is out for blood?
Now, this isn't to say that you should just blindly avoid conflict through this channel.
If the other side sees you showing any weakness, they'll just push even harder.
Instead, it means this channel is best used purely as a deterrent.
We must be prepared for the worst-case scenario, even if it means fighting a lawsuit until we're bankrupt.
and my determination to see this through to the very end.
But we know this is a way to get both sides to weigh the costs, take a step back, and settle the matter peacefully.
The last line of the Judgment for the Lawsuit Hexagram, 'It is beneficial to see the great man, but not to cross the great river,' also serves to elaborate on what to do.
When it comes to a dispute, it doesn't necessarily have to end up in court.
Even if both sides have already lost their cool and are ready for a fight to the death,
you can still try a different approach.
Find a fair and reputable authority figure to act as a mediator and make the ruling.
This is precisely the line from the Commentary on the Tuan.
It is beneficial to meet a great man, for this upholds what is central and correct.
Now, on the surface, this term 'uprightness and impartiality' seems to be about credibility.
But in reality, the deeper meaning behind it is more about...
Find a powerful figure who is respected, or even commands authority, by both sides.
Otherwise, neither side would acknowledge that this prominent figure is 'upright and impartial'.
When two sides are at a stalemate, it's a classic clash of titans.
Once a third party is brought in, it creates some room to maneuver.
Perhaps both sides had wanted to reconcile all along.
But they're just too proud to back down.
In this situation, the third party's role is to provide a way for both sides to save face.
As long as someone can step in and make that transition,
In the end, it's even possible for both sides to turn enemies into friends.
Even if we're the ones taking the hit,
As long as you can eventually get to the stage where 'no discord, no concord' becomes a reality,
In fact, this is a good thing, a sign of fortune.
Just think of the costs you've incurred as money spent to ward off disaster.
Whatever you do, don't get bogged down in endless arguments.
If, when it comes to disputes, you were to act as in the previous hexagram,
to take the risk and 'cross the great river'
insisting on taking that risk,
So, whether it means fighting a lawsuit to the bitter end, or resorting to desperate measures and even violence,
your ultimate fate will certainly be a bad one.
So, what we've discussed so far is that even when you're in the right, you should still avoid disputes.
let alone when you're the one in the wrong.
If you've done something wrong and are now being held accountable,
If you're wrong, admit you're wrong.
Pay what you owe in compensation, and ask for forgiveness where it's due.
If their asking price is too high, just say, 'In that case, let's just take it to the authorities.'
Then just say, 'Alright, let's take it to the authorities.'
Use the cost of going to court to scare them, making them weigh the pros and cons.
It is better to make friends than enemies.
We absolutely must avoid taking a lawsuit all the way to the bitter end.
And it's just as the saying goes: in ancient times, it didn't matter if you were the plaintiff or the defendant.
Regardless of who wins or loses, there are no real winners. The only winner is the government.
Looking at the entire hexagram of 'Conflict' and its major lines,
The only line that is both in its correct position and centered is the ninth five, which symbolizes the government.
You really have to savor the profound meaning behind this!
The Commentary on the Decision says, "In the end, it is inauspicious. A lawsuit cannot be won."
We must always remember, this doesn't mean that a dispute can't ultimately be won or succeed.
It's not that you can never succeed in a dispute,
or that you can't win.
Instead, it's about the act of arguing itself.
There is no such thing as true success to begin with!
Don't think you're untouchable just because you have connections in the government.
Just because you're powerful, you think you can wield the judicial system like a butcher's knife and just hack away at people as you please.
First, your reputation will be ruined.
Second, the people you victimize aren't necessarily pushovers.
Once you make an enemy, they will hunt you to the ends of the earth.
Even the most humble person, as long as they keep their eyes open at all times,
Sooner or later, they'll seize the chance to get their revenge on the most powerful people!
During the Su Jun Rebellion, Huan Yi defended Jingcheng for a year.
He was ultimately killed by the rebel general, Han Huang.
Han Huang was defeated and killed.
However, Jiang Bo, the magistrate of Jingcheng at the time, was also involved in Huan Yi's murder.
At the time, the magistrate of the capital, Jiang Bo, was also involved.
And so, the fifteen-year-old Huan Wen, with a heart full of grief and a burning desire for revenge, vowed to avenge his father.
However, Jiang Bo was an official of the imperial court.
But Huan Wen held back.
Three years later, Jiang Bo died.
Jiang Bo died.
At the funeral, Huan Wen killed Jiang Bo's three sons.
Huan Wen killed Jiang Bo's three sons.
Huan Wen held the imperial court in awe.
This act of avenging his kinsmen with such composure later became a model of virtue for the young men of the Eastern Jin Dynasty.
When the lawsuit finally reaches its end,
The feud between the two sides had, in fact, escalated far beyond the original incident.
And this escalating hatred will plunge both families into an endless, inescapable hell!
Regardless of who wins or loses, both sides will be financially drained.
And on top of that, they would have to bear the endless future costs of guarding against revenge!
In ancient times, one had to maintain a constant sense of awe and reverence towards lawsuits.
You should even see it as a terrifying beast! The government isn't there to give you justice or clear your name.
He's a living King of Hell who devours people without spitting out the bones!
Litigation should only be used as a deterrent.
The best way forward is to know when to stop, as it's better to resolve a feud than to escalate it.
If you pursue litigation to the bitter end, everything will turn out badly!
This line from the Xiang Zhuan, "Heaven and water move in different directions, giving rise to the image of contention. The superior person, in his undertakings, plans the beginning."
This once again serves as a warning about the core principle of this hexagram.
Heaven moves westward, while water flows eastward.
This hexagram is inherently about moving in opposite directions.
When it comes to this matter of contention,
A noble person must "plan for the beginning when starting a task."
In other words, you have to plan for the beginning right from the very start.
Define the rules and clarify the boundaries in advance.
So, from the very root of the matter, you must do everything possible to avoid reaching the point of litigation.
as a guiding principle for how we conduct ourselves in life.
Now, let's look at the line statements. The lower trigram of the 'Dispute' hexagram is 'Kǎn', which represents danger.
This means that right from the start, it's fraught with danger.
The first six, a yin line, is in a yang position, which is an improper placement.
This position, which should be occupied by a strong, masculine force, is instead taken by a soft, feminine one from the very beginning.
but instead, it's handled with a soft and yielding approach from the very beginning.
The very beginning of the Song Hexagram serves as a reminder that its core principle is to be prudent and avoid litigation.
This is the core tenet of the Song hexagram.
Do not prolong the matter; though there is some talk, it will ultimately be auspicious.
In the phrase '不永所事', '永' means 'long-lasting' or 'permanent'.
Here, "yong" means to be long-lasting or to continue for a long time.
This line from the hexagram means...
Do not get bogged down in a dispute that has just arisen.
Don't blow small things out of proportion.
Do not be the first to initiate a lawsuit.
Even if you're in the right, it's best to cut your losses and stop the conflict as soon as possible.
The commentary in the Xiang Zhuan states: 'Do not persist in the matter of litigation, for it cannot be prolonged.'
Disputes should not be prolonged.
This kind of dispute absolutely cannot be allowed to drag on.
We've already covered the reasons for this.
Once your case is on the government's record,
and closing the case is no longer up to you.
From the county magistrate, his advisors, and the clerks, to the bailiffs and runners...
If you fail to grease the palm of even one of them,
They have what you might call a 'legal right to harm' you. Even if it's just summoning you back and forth to 'discuss the case'.
Can you take the heat?
And that's not even mentioning if the other side is throwing a lot of money at the problem.
They can even fabricate evidence to completely destroy you!
“Minor complaints, but ultimate good fortune.”
Even if it means swallowing their pride just to keep the peace,
You'll be mocked by the onlookers.
But we jumped out of the black hole of controversy from the very beginning.
This prevents the endless drain and potential disaster that come with an escalating conflict.
This allows us to focus our resources, energy, and time on expanding the pie.
A noble person asks about disaster, not fortune. For a noble person, the absence of disaster is fortune itself.
The Xiang Zhuan says, "Although there are minor disagreements, it is through these that clarity is achieved."
The text says 'to clarify', not 'to win the argument'.
not to win the argument.
When a conflict arises between two parties,
Let's sit down and lay all the cards on the table.
Clarify the facts and explain the reasoning.
I took a loss, but I know you didn't do it on purpose.
I'll do you the favor, let's just avoid this in the future.
If you've taken a loss, I'll give you fair compensation.
Forget about winning or losing, it's all about the interests. That's it.
But when it's about winning or losing, people get emotional.
Who's right or wrong doesn't matter.
But when you boil it down to the actual benefits and do the math,
and all that anger just melts away.
If you gotta pay, you pay. If you gotta haggle, you haggle. It's all about the money, right?
Besides, it's not like we're pushovers who just let people walk all over us.
or just let you walk all over us.
We're not afraid to face the law or even a knife fight, and we'll take full responsibility for our actions.
But what's the point of us both ending up losers? There's no point.
Let's just talk it out.
We'll be seeing a lot of each other down the road, so we've got to keep things friendly to make money, right?
The vast majority of disasters and internal conflicts stem from the endless escalation of trivial matters.
When any conflict arises, your first instinct should always be to prevent it from escalating.
Always remember: seek profit, not a fight. Address the issue, not the person.
Once the truth is discerned, stop there, and you will ultimately achieve good fortune.
Now, for the second line, let's look at its statement.
If you cannot win the dispute, retreat and flee.
The three hundred households in his town will be free from blame.
The character '克' (kè) here means 'to be capable of' or 'to be competent for'.
It does not imply retreat.
The original meaning of the character "shěng" is a film or opacity growing over the eye.
and by extension, it came to mean disaster.
The meaning of this line is...
If you can't hold back from that first step,
the lawsuit is inevitable.
But if you have a hunch that you're simply no match for them in terms of resources and status in this conflict,
Continuing will lead to certain defeat.
Then you must stop the confrontation immediately.
Just bite the bullet, sheathe your锋芒, and retreat to a place where you pose no threat.
The character '窜' (cuàn) in this line from the Xiang Zhuan, 'Unable to win the lawsuit, he flees and escapes,' is particularly well-chosen.
It's a perfect description.
It means making a swift and decisive retreat, as fast as possible.
The phrase 'a fief of two hundred households' refers to the smallest landed estate granted to a junior minister in the pre-Qin period.
It was the smallest fiefdom size, posing the least threat.
This shows an attitude of conceding defeat.
as long as you can pull back in time to cut your losses,
we can still protect our last remaining asset.
And this stronghold you've retreated to will no longer pose a threat to your adversary.
and won't pose a threat to your opponent in the dispute.
This is also a way to show, through your actions, that you've completely surrendered.
This way, you can avoid disaster, settle the score, and preserve your vital resources.
When many people run into conflicts and disputes,
Even when they know they can't win,
but are dragged down and ultimately destroyed by their own pride.
All because they can't swallow their pride, they insist on fighting to the bitter end.
Ultimately, they exhaust all their time, energy, and resources.
dragging their families down with them, and even losing their lives in the process.
When we were discussing 'The Mirror of Rise and Fall'...
We've talked about how big corporations use lawsuits to bleed out and crush small businesses.
When we were discussing the second line of the Qian hexagram, 'A dragon appearing in the field is favorable to see the great man',
and we said something similar when discussing the line 'A dragon appearing in the field is favorable to meet the great man'.
If you're being squeezed out by a 'great man',
then you need to find another 'great man' to rescue you.
So, in this situation, let's say you're a small company...
What if you get targeted by a big corporation before you're even ready?
He's just going to bleed you dry and drag you to your death.
So, swallow your pride and negotiate an acquisition with them immediately.
If he refuses, it means he's out to destroy you.
Then go talk to their competitor about an acquisition.
Save as many resources as you possibly can.
At this point, the core objective is to minimize losses as much as possible.
As long as our price is lower than the market price,
Whether it's the company that's trying to harm us, or its competitors,
will be interested in acquiring us.
And so, we were able to 'return and save our three hundred households from harm'.
three hundred households
We've managed to pull ourselves out of the vortex of confrontation.
Maybe we did sell it for a pittance.
Perhaps the future prospects were snuffed out.
But at least we've saved our skin.
There will be other opportunities in the future.
After the "Dragon in the Field" fails to "see the great man,"
It's not like you're the Leaping Dragon, destined to be crushed to pieces.
Just go back to being a 'Hidden Dragon' and start all over again!
Never assume that just because you're in the right, you have to pursue justice.
In ancient times, if you were an adult and still believed in things like justice and truth,
That just means you've never really grown up.
This line from the Xiang Zhuan is the most sobering of all.
When the lower disputes with the higher, disaster is imminent.
At best, it's just a token gesture of praise.
When it comes to conflict, it's not really about who's right or wrong.
Instead, it's simply a matter of weighing the strengths and weaknesses of the opposing sides.
Being in the lower trigram means you're the weaker party.
If you, being in a lower position, decide to contend with those above you,
challenging the strong as the weak.
When there's a complete imbalance in status, power, and resources,
and still insist on taking them to court.
In that case, you have no one to blame but yourself for the trouble that follows.
The vast majority of disasters,
Or they're brought on by your own stubbornness and competitiveness.
or they stem from our own naivety and delusions, from not knowing when to advance or retreat.
or brought on by not understanding the unwritten rules of the real world. Take our creative ideas, for instance.
The path we've just pioneered might get stolen by a big corporation.
We feel wronged, and we want to fight to the bitter end, but that's just not necessary.
There's just no need for that.
This has been a reality since ancient times: the strong prey on the weak.
We have to face reality.
You're just an Apple, crushed by Microsoft.
Once you rise to the top, you too will become the very dragon you once sought to slay.
Big
Because human nature never changes.
What we need to do is recognize these principles and get things done.
Knowing when to cut your losses and admit defeat is all part of getting things done.
Now, for the third six. Let's look at the line statement: 'Feasting on the old virtue, firmness in danger, and finally, good fortune.'
This means to adhere to established rules and cherish the legacy of your predecessors.
On one hand, this phrase 'enjoying the old virtue' means you should stick to your own duties.
Do not covet benefits or positions that are not rightfully yours.
and not stir up trouble.
and avoid picking fights.
On the other hand, it means that
Even when you find yourself in the middle of a dispute,
Alternatively, you can keep a low profile while seeking out the wisdom and virtues of the older generation.
while also seeking the virtues of the older generation to mediate and communicate.
The core idea is just one thing: to calm things down and make peace. As long as you can stop and cut your losses,
then the crisis will inevitably be resolved.
And the commentary from the 'Xiang Zhuan,' which says, 'Following the established virtues brings good fortune,' is also a very insightful addition.
The addition, 'following the superior,' is also quite insightful.
As the lower trigram, as the subordinate,
Stay true to your own duties and established virtues.
Do not engage in pointless disputes.
Don't go looking for trouble.
These are the rules that those in power expect you to follow.
The higher-ups don't want their subordinates constantly causing trouble for them.
You need to handle the mess yourself.
What the higher-ups expect from you is that you keep your own house in order.
and hand over the profits.
What's emphasized is a state of peace and stability.
But if your superiors see you as a troublemaker,
your journey will come to an end.
When the powers that be see you as someone who only brings profit, not trouble,
and you're only bringing in the profits,
Only then will you become more stable and prosperous.
And purely from a developmental perspective,
The reason we stand out is also because...
the strengthening of our own capabilities and our ability to solve problems.
In an environment rife with controversy,
The safest path is always to stick to the right way and stay true to your own course.
and leave your competitors far behind through steady, daily progress.
While the apes on the banks wail without cease, the light boat has already passed ten thousand mountains.
Development and progress have never been about picking fights or trying to be the strongest.
or how many lawsuits you win,
or winning countless arguments.
Instead, it's about doing your own job well from the very beginning.
and to avoid getting mired in disputes.
The latter part of this line, 'or to serve the king, but without success'...
It also points out the sources of many of our unexpected misfortunes.
We've actually covered this line before, back when we were discussing the third six of the Kun hexagram.
Now, this 'no success' doesn't mean you're incapable of achieving anything.
Instead, it means not claiming credit for your achievements and not being greedy for success.
If we are the ones who get things done,
and then attribute the credit to your superiors.
so as not to overshadow your superior with your achievements.
The third six is a yin line in a yang position, which is an improper placement.
You are at the very heart of the peril.
So, the emphasis of the third six is on 'attributing the achievements of the lower to the higher.'
If you don't understand that 'carrying out the superior's work' is the next best thing,
Evil is bestowed by the superior.
Assessment comes first, action second.
Authority is a gift bestowed by others, and this act of bestowing it is of the utmost importance.
If you don't get the fact that the only way for you to advance is to help your superiors get ahead,
you can truly advance.
this principle
Then you, the little go-getter who takes all the credit, are just asking for trouble.
You'll bring a lot of unwarranted disasters upon yourself.
If you don't yield the credit, the higher-ups have plenty of ways to turn a 'good comrade' like you into a 'bad one'.
And just like that, they'll block your path to advancement.
How did Deng Ai, a hero who conquered a kingdom, get thrown into a prisoner's cart by Zhong Hui in a single day?
thrown into a prison cart in a single move.
How did Shi Wansui, the Turks' worst nightmare, end up being framed by Yang Su and executed in the imperial court?
When you are in a subordinate position, you must always be aware of your place.
Always remember the rules of this world.
Even in the Qian Gua, the second nine line says, 'A dragon appears in the field. It is beneficial to see the great man.'
You need someone to give you a leg up.
Even at the Ninth Two line, you must be vigilant from morning till night, or you'll fail to catch the eye of those above you.
And whatever you do, don't ever think this world is a fair system where your efforts are guaranteed to pay off.
Instead, it's a world where the advantaged destroy the disadvantaged.
Every underdog who rises to the top does so by clinging to the powerful and leveraging their strength.
Liu Bang, before he started, had the backing of the Xiang family.
Before Liu Bang started his rise, he was backed by the Xiang family.
When Liu Xiu entered Hebei, he relied on the Twenty-Eight Generals of Yuntai.
the 28 Generals.
Cao Cao, who fought his way out of the chaos at the end of the Han Dynasty, initially relied on the banner of Yuan Shao and the authority of the Han court.
Build high walls, stockpile grain, and delay proclaiming yourself king.
Even when you are in a position of power, you should still stay away from disputes.
We'll get to that in a moment.
And if you're in a lower position, it's even more crucial to stay away from legal disputes!
The fourth nine, the line statement: 'Not winning the lawsuit, return to the original mandate, change, and be steadfast in what is right. Good fortune.'
Now, the situation for the fourth line is just like the second.
Here, the phrase "unable to win the lawsuit" appears.
But a different position means a different meaning.
In the case of the second nine, it's in the lower trigram, so it represents a subordinate challenging a superior, an inferior confronting a superior.
When the subordinate challenges the superior, the weaker party has no inherent chance of winning.
The fourth line, the Nine-Four, is in the upper trigram, but it is a solid line in a soft position.
This is not its rightful place.
The fourth line, being close to the ruler's position like a high minister, should be humble and obedient to the one above.
However, it's placed at the beginning of the Qian trigram.
This 'failure to win the lawsuit' implies that the strong are bullying the weak.
This means that after gaining power, resources, and a judicial advantage,
and judicial advantage,
They start to actively provoke conflicts and prey on the weak.
But because this goes against the natural order and is not the righteous path,
Even if they gain the upper hand for a time,
But in the end, it will backfire on them.
When a subordinate official provokes the wrath of the masses, those in power will often execute them to appease the people's anger.
Getting rid of those who bully the weak and abuse their power is actually the lowest-cost solution for society.
and the most effective pressure release valve.
And this is exactly what the Ninth Five loves to do.
In our 'Mirror of Rise and Fall' series, we've talked about the tactic of 'using Heaven's name to blame others and hide one's own selfish motives.'
Using the heavens to judge others and conceal one's own selfish motives.
selfish
under the guise of the "Will of Heaven," the "Mandate of Heaven," or "national law,"
and attack their targets in the name of a supreme authority.
exploiting the guise of public justice to conceal their own selfish desires.
and under the guise of 'acting on Heaven's behalf,' forcibly label their opponents as reactionaries.
and "Gaining trust by speaking in the people's name."
in the name of the people, the wishes of the common folk, or the voice of the masses.
and package his own agenda as 'acting in accordance with the will of the people'.
using the voice of the masses to cover up one's autocratic intentions.
and make their own schemes appear to be the choice of the masses.
Never, ever take public opinion lightly.
And when they want to take you down, it's the sharpest knife they have!
Go with the flow, or you'll be branded a rebel.
And once that label is slapped on you, it's no small matter.
And that's no small matter.
Whatever you do, don't become a traitor to the people.
To return to one's destiny, even if it changes, and to remain steadfast and upright brings good fortune.
Here, "复" (fù) means to return, and "渝" (yú) means to change.
I interpret it as the meaning of change.
If those in power who prey on the weak can realize their mistakes,
and are able to turn back from their mistakes and return to the righteous path of the natural order,
in the end, they can still hold fast to the right path and achieve a favorable outcome.
and receive good fortune nine times.
The reason why the fourth nine line should not bully the weak is that...
Because it presents three major hidden dangers for you.
First, the family you've bullied and brought to ruin.
You'll be forging a feud, a vendetta, that will last until one side is utterly destroyed.
And are you so sure you can wipe them out, root and stem?
It's not the theft you should fear, but the thief who's always watching. The cost of being on constant guard is just too high.
Besides, what if he happens to have a brother named Wu Song?
Second, if you go too far...
The Ninth Five, acting on Heaven's behalf, will punish and eliminate you to quell the public's outrage.
All the profits you've made from bullying the weak,
will all become the spoils for the Ninth Five to carry out Heaven's will.
In ancient times,
Confiscating property was a key method for replenishing the national treasury and the emperor's personal coffers.
Third, even though you're in a position of advantage,
But at the end of the day, you're not the one sitting on the throne.
You're not the one who has the final say in everything.
What if your opponent has connections that reach the heavens?
What if the person you've just messed with has someone powerful backing them up, someone you can't afford to cross?
What if it's just a huge coincidence?
Yang Naiwu had a classmate named Wu Yitong.
And Wu Yitong's boss was Hu Xueyan.
And as it turns out, Hu Xueyan also knew Weng Tonghe.
Could it be that someone was trying to use this incident to shake up the imperial court?
So, the point is, even if you're in a position of advantage,
nor should you bully the weak with your power.
And especially, you must never twist the law to harm the innocent!
When it comes to bullying those in a weaker position, they do indeed have an inherent advantage.
For the subordinate to challenge the superior is to invite disaster and flee in disgrace.
If you don't run fast enough, you're going to die a horrible death.
But for the one in power, as long as they are willing to turn back,
That's already giving the victim too much credit.
This is all about returning to the right path.
Change your heart, and disputes will dissolve. Return to the right path, and disaster will vanish.
Return to the right path, and disaster will dissipate.
To recognize and correct one's mistakes is a great virtue.
This is especially true when you're in a position of power and the victim is less fortunate.
Turn back, and you'll have a chance.
The real world already gives those in power so many advantages.
All you have to do is turn back.
Don't be a fool and refuse a good offer.
Ah.
The fifth nine.
The line statement says, 'In litigation, great fortune.' Now, when you see that, don't jump to the conclusion that going to court is a guaranteed win, okay?
that you'll win just by taking the case to court.
But that's not what this line means at all.
The fifth, nine, is the position of the ruler.
It is the position of hearing and adjudicating disputes.
Not the plaintiff or the defendant.
This corresponds to the core line from the hexagram's statement: 'It is beneficial to see a great man.'
This is also further explained by a line from the Tuan Zhuan.
The text says, 'It is advantageous to see the great man, for he upholds centrality and correctness.' This brings us to the Ninth Five, a yang line in a yang position, the ruler's position, and it is also centered.
And it's also the only line in the entire hexagram that's in its correct position. So, what does that tell us?
So, what does this tell us?
But when it comes to debate, it's the one thing that's all gain and no loss for a ruler.
Or to be more precise,
Now, this 'Nine in the Fifth' position isn't just referring to the monarch.
but rather, it refers to the person in power who holds the ultimate authority to make the final decision.
In the county, this Ninth Four line would be like Ximen Qing.
The 9-5 is the county magistrate, and all lawsuits ultimately land on his desk.
Because he's the one who makes the final call.
It's just like the lawsuit between Bai Jingqi from the TV series 'The Grand Mansion Gate' and the Sun family, who stole his medicine formula.
Bai Jingqi had to pay Jiang Wen.
The Sun family was dragged into this endless process and had to keep paying up.
And this endless process meant they had to keep paying up too.
The ones who hold the final say in any dispute are the ones who love it most when you take each other to court.
If there were no lawsuits, then what about his advisors and bookkeepers?
So how were the clerks from the six offices and the bailiffs from the three squads supposed to make a living?
The imperial court only pays the county magistrate's salary!
Take Song Jiang, for example. He was a clerk in the county jail.
And those guys? They didn't get a government salary.
So, what do you think? Was Song Jiang expecting a paycheck from the county magistrate, or was he making his own money?
So,
Of course, it's true that if the dispute reaches the Ninth Five line, the Ninth Five will always come out ahead and never suffer a loss.
But when it comes to making a profit, you still have to distinguish between short-term gains and long-term benefits.
Regarding the line statement's mention of "Dispute, supreme good fortune"...
However,
The Xiang Zhuan further explains that the great fortune in litigation comes from upholding centrality and correctness, which again emphasizes...
the person in power who holds the final authority to make a ruling.
requires a firm and decisive power.
and a heart of impartial fairness, without bias or favor.
The ruling must convince both parties, bringing the dispute to a final and peaceful end.
Ultimately, the dispute is brought to the Nine in the Fifth place.
The fifth nine line, positioned in the correct place of the Qian trigram, the Heaven, observes the subtle and treacherous rights and wrongs of the disputes below.
Its duty is to resolve all disputes under heaven.
This means that all disputes, when they reach this point, can receive a judgment that is acceptable to both parties.
Its purpose is to cease litigation and resolve conflicts at their very source.
Let all zero-sum games and internal conflicts end here.
Once the case is closed, the matter is settled.
rather than inciting even greater violence and bloodshed down the line.
The reason this line is described as 'Yuan Ji'—the highest level of auspiciousness...
This is to say,
The impartial judgment of the fifth nine, the sovereign position holding the power of final decision,
In this case,
and how vital it is for the peace and stability of the people under their jurisdiction!
A fair and impartial judgment can dispel the hostility in society.
It prevents the powerful from wantonly bullying the weak,
and reduce the overall social cost.
and to reverse the contentious and unruly atmosphere within the jurisdiction.
Only then can it be worthy of this fundamental and ultimate auspiciousness—'Great Fortune'!
And this impartial judgment is also the most crucial element when it comes to getting things done, starting a business, and leading a team.
Remember when we were discussing the "Power and Its Application" chapter of the "Art of Power"?
Do you remember how Li Shimin's authority stemmed from his wisdom, his trust from his sincerity, and his success from his harmony?
and that achievement comes from harmony?
But we won't go into all that again here.
If you've forgotten, just go back and check out our video on the Art of Power.
And here, I also need to point out a common misconception.
The term 'zhong zheng' doesn't refer to absolute fairness.
After all, absolute fairness has never existed.
To be precise, this "zhongzheng" actually means finding a compromise.
It's about allowing both sides of a dispute to reach an acceptable outcome.
The core objective is to resolve the conflict.
and bring the matter to a close.
This is just like what happened to Yuchi Gong, who was almost killed by that old guard of the Prince of Qin's mansion, Yin Kaishan, and Qu Jiaotong.
Now, from a standpoint of absolute fairness and justice,
Yin Kaishan and Qu Jiaotong absolutely should have been punished and held accountable.
But Li Shimin didn't punish them.
Because they were the most crucial members of his core team.
Li Shimin, however, chose to balance the scales from a different perspective.
On one hand, he rewarded Yuchi Gong generously to appease him.
On the other hand, he also made Yuchi Gong his personal bodyguard.
From then on, he no longer had to worry about being backstabbed.
At the same time, he also had Yuchi Gong earn military merits.
This also served to humiliate Li Yuanji, proving to the veteran generals why he was so determined to protect this fierce general.
This simple act of fairness was enough to cause the Prince of Qin's household to fall apart.
This caused the Prince of Qin's administration to fall apart.
This made the Prince of Qin seem like someone who favored the new over the old.
and ensure the loyalty of Yuchi Gong.
This left the old guards with no room for complaint, forcing them to work even harder in an increasingly cutthroat environment.
and work even harder in this increasingly competitive environment.
This is the true meaning of the ninth five's centrality and correctness.
Now, let's look at the topmost line, the Ninth Yang. It's a yang line in a yin position, which means it's out of place.
Failing to stop where one should is a sign of obstinacy and self-will.
Let's look at the hexagram statement: 'Perhaps he will be given a fragrant sash.'
The character '锡' is interchangeable with '赐', which means 'to bestow', and '鞶带' refers to a wide, leather belt.
It was part of the official attire for ancient officials.
This line of the hexagram means that those who win through endless disputes,
Even if you temporarily gain the status and rewards bestowed by the ruler,
will also be stripped away in a very short time.
So, to sum it up: endless litigation leads to ruin, and what's granted in the morning is taken away by evening.
The reason this happens is that
This is because your honor and favor are not earned through meritorious deeds,
earned through establishing your words and character.
Instead, it's the result of exhausting all arguments, escalating conflicts to the breaking point, and suffering through a brutal internal struggle.
and won through brutal internal strife.
Its very origin is tainted, and its virtue is unworthy of its position.
And on top of that, this endless litigation process will cause you to lose your very foundation.
and completely drained your own resources.
You're extremely vulnerable to a third party taking advantage of the situation, like the oriole waiting behind the mantis.
Every single step of this lawsuit is just a constant drain on your finances.
No matter how much you're in the right, once a lawsuit drags on for too long,
Whether it's your superiors, your friends and family, or your neighbors,
They'll all start to see you as someone who just stirs up trouble and is constantly surrounded by problems.
This, in fact, is a huge blow to your own reputation.
This is exactly what the 'Xiang Zhuan' says: 'To win a lawsuit and receive an official position is not worthy of respect!'
So, the case is over.
What if another competitor of yours decides to kick you while you're down and files another lawsuit against you?
Do you really have the financial resources and energy to handle another one?
Even if you're not afraid, thinking, 'We're in the right, so who are we scared of?'
But here's the thing...
But the arbiter might not have a very good impression of you.
And they'll think, 'Oh great, you're here to stir up trouble again!'
But that's not even the worst part.
But the most terrifying part is the long-term consequences that stem from a protracted lawsuit.
The losing side will harbor endless, long-term malice and seek revenge!
It could even lead to the annihilation of your entire family!
Let's take this a step further, to the victory in a bitter lawsuit.
This is also the ultimate fate of all factional strife.
All factional conflicts stem from initial disputes that were not properly resolved.
One side, with the emperor's backing, secured a temporary victory.
The emperor, however, failed to follow the path of the central and correct ninth five to settle and stop the dispute.
As a result, the losing side feels they've suffered a great injustice and taken a huge loss.
What follows is an increasingly messy and tangled cycle of mutual retaliation.
The entire Hexagram of Litigation, in essence, serves to remind us of one fundamental principle.
Success is built on strength and a solid foundation.
Engaging in disputes is an act that endlessly drains our strength and foundation.
Even if the strong prevail over the weak and win a protracted lawsuit,
But the resulting costs down the line are simply incalculable.
Therefore, it is essential to cease litigation and end disputes.
Traveling light is the path to good fortune.
The Hexagram of Xu represents the principle of sustenance.
Where there is the provision of food and drink, there is bound to be contention. Therefore, it is followed by the hexagram 'Conflict'.
And where there are disputes, there must be a great arbiter.
And conflict must be followed by the military.
The Xù Hexagram is about the competition for and distribution of resources.
Because resources are always finite,
If you get your hands on it, it means someone else didn't.
And this is what leads to conflict.
And this leads to the hexagram of Lawsuit.
So, with the Lawsuit Hexagram, if the litigation process is taken to its very end and still doesn't stop...
Ultimately, the conflict escalates.
And that's how more and more people get dragged into the conflict.
Both sides start calling for backup, and a full-scale battle begins.
Another nearly 40,000 words, just to marvel at the great wisdom of our ancestors.
In our next episode, we'll dive into the Hexagram of the Army, and explore the dynamics of group conflict!